All right, here we are. Season one, episode one of Concord Storytellers, and we are not
dipping our toes in the water. We're starting with one of the heavyweights from Concord, Massachusetts,
both in terms of guest and topic. We have renowned historian Richard Smith and Henry David Thoreau. Am I saying that correctly? Thoreau,
yes. Thoreau, not Thoreau. No, get it right. If you're coming to Concord, get it right.
The Wikipedia article has four alternate pronunciations and instructs you on which one is correct.
So I'm guessing you had a part in that. When I first moved to Concord in 99 to be a historian
here in town, I was a ranger at the National Park. I had started doing living history as
Thoreau. And this woman came up to me who had been here all of her life and she said,
if you're going to be this guy, you better learn to pronounce his name correctly. And
I'm like, whoops. Which of course, I'm from Akron, Ohio. I had no idea. So we always said
Thoreau. So now when I say it that way, it actually sounds kind of strange. But yes,
we do know that it is Thoreau. His grandfather was a French Huguenot shipwrecked in 1773,
picked up by a British frigate, brought to Boston. In 1773, you do not want to have a
French name in a British city like Boston. So it was Jean Thoreau or Thoreau. And we
think that's about when he changed his name, at least the pronunciation, to John Thoreau.
He changed the spelling because nobody could read back then. But illiteracy was pretty
high. But John Thoreau was then Henry Thoreau's dad's name. And then his older brother was
John Thoreau. And Bronson Alcott said that Thoreau is well named because he is so Thoreau.
And also Nathaniel Hawthorne, when he first met him, he spelled in his journal, Dined
with Mr. Thoreau, and he spelled it T-H-O-R-O-W. So that's a smoking gun.
We know we are correct then.
We know we are correct. So our job in Concord is to go out and spread the word that everybody
that comes to Concord, you can tell somebody is not from the area when they say Thoreau
and they say Concord.
Right. Yeah. That's how I said it when I moved here. I grew up in Michigan and Tennessee
and I didn't know how to say anything. I was saying not only Concord but Worchester.
Worchester, Glauchester.
Yeah. I didn't know how to say anything. But now it flows. I can actually say things correctly.
Right. When I say Thoreau, it just comes out and I'll be talking to visitors or whomever
and I'll say Thoreau, Thoreau, and they'll stop me almost every time and say, I notice
you're saying this differently. So I go through the whole shtick that I just went through
with you. So if it sounded really well practiced.
Yeah. I can tell you've done that a few times.
Yeah. Just a couple. Yeah.
So living historian. So I think you really, it sounds like you really help people kind
of immerse themselves in what life was like in Thoreau's time.
Absolutely.
What was Concord like when he was born here?
He was.
What was it like? What was the town like? What were people doing? Take us back in time.
So Thoreau was born over on the Virginia Road at his grandmother's farmhouse on July 12,
1917, about the time that he was born. And then when he died in 1862, Concord was always
around 2000 people, primarily a small farming town, just like every other small farming
town around here. You had Boston, which was the big city. You had Worcester, which was
a fairly good size city. And then in between, you had all of these small towns, Concord,
Sudbury, Wayland, Acton, Bedford, Hudson. They were all basically small farming towns.
Concord was no different than any of the other towns.
But it had, you know, around that time, all these prominent figures and authors that you
mentioned, Alcott, Emerson.
That was coming.
So that was coming. So he was born there, but that wasn't established yet.
No.
So when did that happen?
So that happened in the 1840s. I was going to say the main claim to fame to Concord in
1817 was the fact that the American Revolution started here.
And in Lexington, of course. But because of the Battle of Concord on April 19th, 1775,
that's the one thing, at least in those early 19th century, that kind of set Concord apart
from all of these other towns.
So the battlefield was here. Every year they would have what became eventually Patriots
Day and they would bring out the old veterans and they would have parades and basically
doing what we do now on Patriots Day here in town.
So that was our main claim to fame. By the 1830s, 1835, 1836, Ralph Waldo Emerson was
living here.
So Thurow and Emerson are in the same town at the same time. 1840, the Alcotts moved
here. 1842, Nathaniel Hawthorne moves here.
So that's really when it starts to become this literary hub as opposed to just being
the place where the American Revolution started.
Got it. So it was a small draw because it was kind of cool that you had all these activities
and festivities happening every year. But then a couple of these famous authors started
to plant roots here and then it just kind of became a draw and escalated from there.
Right. And that's all because of Ralph Waldo Emerson.
Okay.
So Emerson's related to some of the first founders of the town, the Balkleys. And his
grandfather was over at the Old Manse and he was part of the Battle of Concord. And
although Emerson was born in Boston, he considered Concord his ancestral home. And so he moved
here in 1834, lived for a year at the Old Manse where he wrote his first book, Nature,
bought his house over on the Cambridge Turnpike in 1835. And he was here for the rest of his
life till he died in 1882. He wanted to create a literary scene. So the Alcotts are here
because of him. Hawthorne kind of sort of ended up here because of him. But all these
other writers and poets and philosophers and assorted oddballs, they're all coming to Concord
because of Ralph Waldo Emerson. The fact that he and Thoreau are here at the same time is
just really great historical coincidence.
Okay. Got it. And for Thoreau, I mean, looking in his background, his father was a pencil
maker.
He was.
For a living. What was life like growing up here for him?
For Henry, they were pretty poor, actually. So he's born in 1817. His dad had had several
jobs. He was a grocer for a while. The first eight months of his life was over on Virginia
Road. They then moved into another place in Concord. They then lived in Chelmsford for
a while where his dad was a grocery store clerk. Eventually moved to Boston and then
back to Concord. But his dad had a hard time really kind of making a go of various occupations.
Thoreau's uncle Charles had discovered a graphite mine up in New Hampshire and started
this making pencils. And so in 1824, 25, somewhere around there, he asked John Thoreau if he
would be part of this pencil making company, which he did. And then Uncle Charles dropped
out. So by the late 1820s, it was John Thoreau pencils. Eventually became John Thoreau and
sons.
Got it. And so Henry David, it was David Henry originally, right?
He was.
So he's growing up, sort of sounds like sort of his early teenage years. This is starting
to happen. How does he become, you know, he eventually goes to Harvard to study. Like
what, how does he kind of get into this literary and sort of quasi political mindset?
Sure. Well, that comes from his mom, his mom. We know a great deal about both of his parents,
but his mom was very much involved in social reforms of the day and his sister. So there
were four Thoreau kids. There was Helen born in 1812, John Jr. 1815, Henry 1817, Sophia
1819. All of the kids from what we understand were absolutely brilliant. And because of their
mom very much involved in reforms of the day, especially antislavery. So he came from a reform
minded house where mom was involved in not only the antislavery society, but the charitable
society where they would help poor people. So he kind of grew up in that kind of atmosphere
of being socially aware and being socially involved. Right on. And how does he end up
studying at Harvard and what happens when he goes there? So Harvard in 1833 when he
went, he was 16 when he went to college. He's a little bit older than most Harvard boys
at the time. And when I say boys, I mean boys. Harvard was strictly for boys. And so, and
it was about $180 a year at the time when in 1833 the average laborer is making between
30 and 50 cents a day. So $180, $190 a year is a lot of money. So the people that are
going to Harvard tend to be the well off people, sons of doctors, sons of lawyers. Thoreau
is not any of those guys, but they really insisted, mom and dad really insisted that
at least one of the boys go to college. Henry was sent over his brother supposedly because
he was a better scholar. They didn't want to waste their money, I guess. So, but you're
going to go to Harvard for one of four reasons. Doctor, lawyer, minister, teacher. Thoreau
became a teacher. He was 16, graduated at 20, middle of his class. He, you know, he
wasn't showing off. He wasn't dropping behind. He's just kind of in the middle there. But
he was a teacher briefly in Concord. And then he and his brother John opened their own private
academy for a couple of years. But by 1843 or so, they were done with that. John died
from from lockjaw, sadly, at the age of 26. So Thoreau's teaching career only lasted a
couple of years. By then, he had met Ralph Waldo Emerson. After he graduated in 1837,
he met Emerson. And really, I think that's when he decided he sees this guy who's writing
essays and giving lectures. And I think that's what kind of decided where he decided, well,
that's kind of what I want to do, too. Okay, so Emerson was a huge influence on him. Absolutely.
And he's done teaching. How does he make this transition into writing Walden? I mean, his
most famous, so I, you know, full disclosure, before reading the Wikipedia article yesterday,
I just knew the line items from high school. I knew that he had written Walden. I've been
to the museum. I am sort of a very, very baseline knowledge here. So he's a teacher. What happens?
So there's a huge difference between the Henry Thoreau that just graduated from college in
1837 to the guy that writes Walden in 1854. It's a, you know, like any of our lives, it's
a progression. And hopefully, throughout your life, you're growing a little bit more. Once
he decided that he was going to be a writer or a man of letters, as he says, the best
thing that happened to him was he was hanging out with Ralph Waldo Emerson. Okay. Emerson
is, Emerson was always finding young men and young women who he thought was going to be
the next great genius, the next great writer or poet or philosopher or whatever. And he
would always really tout these people and he would introduce them to each other. He
would introduce them to people in Cambridge, in Boston. I think that he really felt that
Thoreau was probably the best one out of all of those people. And he had really high hopes
for him. And in those early days, 1837, 38, 39, he's really introducing Thoreau as the
man of Concord. And he would say, oh, you have to meet this guy, this young friend of
mine. Thoreau was 14 years younger. So you have to meet this kid. You know, he's funny
and he's brilliant and he has these nature observations. They would go for walks and
Thoreau was pointing stuff out, the trees and the plants and the birds and the birdsong
and the moss. And Emerson is just completely enraptured by all of this. So he's the one
that kind of gets Thoreau to start keeping a journal in 1837. He says, what are you doing?
Why aren't you keeping a journal? So Thoreau keeps a journal because of Emerson. And that's
where he starts to write down his observations. Fast forward over the years, a lot of those
observations that he would put down in his journal eventually became his lectures and
his essays and even Walden in 1854.
That's fascinating. So I mean, this is, you know, kind of squaring this with how I think
about, you know, I go on walks around Concord all the time. If I'm walking with some, I
am not a naturalist. If I'm walking with someone who's pointing out everything as I walk through
the woods, I kind of zone out. I say that's really, well, this person really knows what
they're talking about. Emerson is one of those people who can say this is a talent that this
person has. This person is very engaged with nature and he helps Henry channel that into
something that is significant and actually can be useful in the world.
Absolutely. You know, I can imagine them walking through the woods and Thoreau is doing this
thing and pointing stuff out and Emerson saying to him, great, write it down.
Yeah. And then he would never have thought to do that before. Probably he wasn't around
people who knew how to capture that gift.
Well, and this is a good period. So the 1830s into the 1840s is a good period for people
like Emerson and Thoreau because you have people who are now traveling the country earning
a living as lecturers.
Okay.
You know, this is something that starts in the 1820s. The Lyceum movement starts here.
I think it was in Medford in Massachusetts in the 1820s. The Concord Lyceum started in
1939 and basically every winter from say October to March or April, the farmers and shopkeepers
of Concord would go to the first parish church or the town hall or one of the school buildings
and they would hear lectures. And these lectures would more often than not be from people who
are out of town who are traveling around the Northeast or even around the country lecturing
on whatever subject they're known for.
So you have scientists and biologists and doctors and historians and naturalists all
kind of coming to these small farming towns and you might not be interested in what they
have to say but everybody else is going to go so why not?
It's something to do. There are no movies to go see.
Absolutely.
There are no concerts to go in.
Especially in the wintertime.
And that's why the Lyceum is in the winter because of the entire year the least amount
of work by farmers is done in the wintertime. So that's why it's being done in the winter.
So people like Emerson and others, this kind of becomes their job. Emerson had lots of
books published and lots of poetry published. He made much more money as a lecturer than
he did as an author or a writer. So this is a good time because Thoreau is seeing Emerson
do this and he's going to Emerson's lectures and I'm sure he's thinking, well gosh, if
he can do it, I can do it too.
Now the only problem is Thoreau hated lecturing. He was not a big fan of it.
Why? Did he not like public speaking?
By all accounts from what we understand he was really bad at it.
He tended, now these are the days before microphones of course, he wasn't very good at enunciating
very loudly. We understand that he would often hold his lecture and he always read his lecture
just as Emerson did. He would hold it up really close to his face and if you're sitting at
First Parish Church and you're in the back row and this guy's up front and he's reading
into his papers, you're not going to hear very much. He's not very demonstrative. Some
of these orators of the day, people like Henry Clay and others, Henry Ward Beecher, the famous
preacher from New York, they were very demonstrative.
Performers.
Absolutely. Emerson was kind of a performer although from what we understand he had very
forceful voice but he wasn't particularly active while he was speaking.
Because he was reading it.
Exactly.
That's a big difference.
But he would raise his hand or he would punch his hand into his fist or pound his hand onto
the lectern or something like that. Thoreau was not really doing any of that stuff and
he was probably socially awkward in a lot of ways from what we understand. He didn't
really like being around people. If he had something that he felt that he needed to say,
he had no trouble lecturing on it. And also like Emerson, he would try out some of his
stuff in front of a live audience just to see if it worked or not. The first chapter
of Walden actually started as a lecture and he lectured it and gave the lecture a bunch
of times, not only here but other places. So he's seeing how it worked but he's not
particularly crazy about being in front of the people.
Yeah. So some of these people who are falling asleep in the back of the first parish church
during his lectures would be probably shocked that we are talking about him in 2024 as a
prominent figure in Concord history.
We actually have there is a guy, I think it was in Lincoln, the town of Lincoln might
have been or some other town around here. Thoreau was reading his essay Walking, which
from 1850 to 57 or so, 59, Thoreau gave that lecture more than any other. And he would
see what worked and what didn't work and eventually it was published after he died. But today
Walking is considered one of Thoreau's, one of his big hits. Everybody loves the essay.
A guy, a young man went to see him read Walking and he says in his journal that he fell asleep
during it. So yeah, people were falling asleep. So Thoreau would lecture when he had to but
he was not crazy about it. And he didn't want to be famous. Emerson was always trying to
get this guy to be famous. And Thoreau in his lifetime really had no interest in that.
Sure.
Again, a lot of it is because he wants to do his own thing. He wants to be by himself.
He likes his solitude. He's much happier going for his walks every day in the woods. He's
much happier hanging out with his family. And he and his family were incredibly close.
Yeah. So that's something I was wondering. You know, you mentioned his brother passing
at 26 years old. I have to imagine if he's that close to his family that has to affect
him and his work and his day to day life.
Yeah. So John was the first one of the family to pass away in January of 1842. And it really
shook Thoreau greatly. He and John were the best of friends. The famous trip they took
was in 1839. They built their own rowboat. They rode from Concord, Massachusetts to Concord,
New Hampshire and then walked to the White Mountains from there. It was a 13 day excursion.
After John dies, a couple of years later, Thoreau moves to Walden Pond. He's writing
his first book. That book is A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers about that boating
trip. So it had a huge impact on Thoreau in the sense that his first book is completely
dedicated to his brother John. It bombed when it was published, but that's a whole other
story. But then Helen dies. Helen Thoreau dies in 1849 from tuberculosis. So really,
after 1850, it's Henry and his sister Sophia and their mom and dad. And Henry and his sister
Sophia were incredibly close. And she was absolutely brilliant in her own way. She was
an incredible botanist. And after he dies in 1862, she becomes his literary executor
and books like Cape Cod and Maine Woods are published because of Sophia.
Got it. So you talk about him sort of seeking this isolation and kind of being away from
people. He obviously achieves that at Walden Pond. Can you talk a bit about how that when
that happens, how that happens, what the process was for him there and going deep into the
woods? He had been thinking about it for quite some
time. When he was at Harvard, one of his classmates, Charles Stearns Wheeler, actually built a
small cabin over near one of the ponds here in Lincoln or next door in Lincoln and Thoreau.
And he spent the summer there. And so that kind of stuck with Thoreau. And after he graduated
from Harvard, moves back to Concord, he meets Emerson as early as like 1840, 1839. Thoreau's
writing in his journal. I want to find a place where I can live by myself and do my writing.
He's living at mom and dad's house and dad's making pencils with help. He has a couple
of Irish boys and mom is keeping borders. And it's not really the most conducive place
for writing. So he needs to find a Garrett of some sort or a writer's retreat. So Emerson
buys some property over at Walden Pond in the fall of 1844. And everybody knew about
Thoreau's wishes, his family, his friends. And so Emerson basically says, I've got this
land. You want to go out there? And Thoreau says, sure. And that's what led to it. Again,
it would not have happened without Ralph Waldo Emerson.
Wow. Right. Sort of the patron saint of...
He was the patron saint of everybody. He gave Henry money and jobs. He gave the Alcotts
money and jobs. Emerson was pretty successful and pretty well off. He also inherited a lot
of money from his first wife when she died. So he was pretty comfortable and he had absolutely
no problem with sharing his money with people who he thought needed it, like Thoreau or
the Alcotts. So because of Emerson, Thoreau's living at Walden Pond. He builds his house.
He's there for a lot of reasons. He's there to write his first book. He's there to simplify
his life. He really wants to kind of... After a lot of people graduate from college, we
do stuff like we travel Europe or we go backpacking across country. When I graduated, I went to
New York for two years. I think that even though it's a few years after college, the
two years at Walden Pond was kind of like Thoreau's growing up and discovering himself,
period. The Henry Thoreau of 1844 is completely different in my mind from the Henry Thoreau
of 1848 when he's done living at Walden Pond. He becomes a much better writer. He becomes
a much better observer of nature. He becomes much better at science, figuring out why stuff
works, why do the trees do this? So just the Henry Thoreau that we know now and who we
honor and who we're talking about, he became that Henry Thoreau while living at Walden
Pond.
Yeah. Yeah. It sounded like, too, I mean, well, for one, he went to college young, 16,
and he probably didn't really fit in with a lot of his classmates. So he probably didn't
really discover himself at college. And in fact, I saw a story about how to get his diploma
from Harvard, they were going to charge him $5 for the... And he refused to pay it because
he said the sheep can keep their skins.
Right. That's the way it worked out.
He didn't sound super impressed with his experience in college.
Yeah. So he received his bachelor, what was called a bachelor of arts degree. And again,
he was a doctor, lawyer, minister, or teacher. Back then, a few years, I think it was like
five years after you graduate, if you're still around and you're still alive and you pay
Harvard $5, you get your master's degree, which it was still that easy, right? And so,
and he thought, well, no, I didn't do anything for it. Just the fact that I'm still around
and I paid my $5. So that's exactly what he did.
He saw it as a money grab.
Yeah, that's exactly what it was. And he was not a proud Harvard graduate. He said that
he learned more in the two years that he lived at Walden Pond than the four years that he
wasted in Cambridge. The famous story is Emerson, also a Harvard graduate, was very proud of
being a Harvard graduate. And he said that Harvard teaches all of the branches of education,
to which Thurlow replied, yes, but none of the roots. So he kind of thought that Harvard
was a waste of his time. The only reason he went was because he was 16 and mom and dad
said, you're going to Harvard.
Yeah.
And yeah.
Okay, well, yeah, I'm 16.
Sure went out.
Yeah.
He hated being in Cambridge. He would walk home many weekends from Cambridge to Concord.
He preferred being in Concord. Yeah, he would go to Cambridge even as he got older in life.
He wouldn't go to Cambridge or Boston all that often. He would go occasionally, but
he preferred as he'd say, I usually leave cities more willingly than I go into them.
So he just didn't really like big places.
So you mentioned a lot of these works that, you know, he's a few people are falling asleep
at his lectures, his books bomb when they're released. He's obviously very famous now.
Did any of that hit while he was still alive or is most of it posthumous?
That's well, the fame is definitely after he died. Yeah, absolutely. He dies in 1862,
May 6th, 1862 at the age of 44. He'd only had two books published. He'd only lectured
seventy five times and he'd had a handful of essays published in various periodicals.
He's just beginning to maybe be famous when he dies in 1862. Not too long before he died,
Bronson Alcott actually wrote an article for the Atlantic called The Forester about Thurow.
And Emerson was even in later years, Emerson was still kind of trying to push him and Walden
did OK. The first book bombed horribly. Walden did OK when it was published in 1854, but
it took him five years to sell out those two thousand copies, you know, compared to something
like Uncle Tom's Cabin. I think in the first six months, Uncle Tom's Cabin did something
like five hundred thousand copies, I mean, some outrageous amount. So Thurow is really
under the literary radar. He's not as famous as Emerson. He's not as famous as Hawthorne.
And so that's kind of starting. But in 1862, when he dies, he's actually becoming better
known as a naturalist than as a writer or as a transcendentalist or an abolitionist.
As I said earlier, because of his sister, Sophia, The Maine Woods was published, Cape
Cod was published. They published a book called Excursions, which is a bunch of his travel
essays. So his publisher, Tickner and Fields and his sister, they really kind of keep his
name alive in the 1860s going into the 1870s. But, you know, if you go to the Boston Public
Library, you walk into the one section and up on the ceiling, there are all these names.
There's Emerson and there's Longfellow and Whittier and Hawthorne and even people like
Francis Parkman, the historian, but there's no Thurow up there. So this area, Concord,
Boston, Massachusetts, he's not really on anybody's on anybody's list of the great
writers. A friend of his, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, abolitionist and writer, he actually
thought, well, maybe we should try to get Thurow's journals published. And so he came
to the Concord to talk to Sophia about getting them published. And he went to a couple of
people who had money. And one of the people he asked said, well, the main question is,
why would anybody want to read Thurow's journals? Who cares? So that didn't happen until like
1906. But it's really the late 19th century. Leo Tolstoy read him and thought, why aren't
Americans reading this guy? 1906, a guy named Mohandas Gandhi read Civil Disobedience and
said, oh, I'm doing this in South Africa. This is what I'm doing. So it's really the
early 20th century that Thurow's kind of starting to gain fame, at least in America. By the
1950s, you have people like Jack Kerouac talking about him and reading him. Supposedly, when
Kerouac went on the road, he took, I think he took a week on the Concord and Merrimack
Rivers with him, maybe Walden. In fact, Kerouac said that he wanted to be a Thurow of the
mountains. So you've got people like him. And then in the 1960s, the counterculture,
the hippies all discovered him and kind of made him the poster child. Thurow protested
the Mexican War. The hippies are protesting the Vietnam War. The environmental movements
really starting in the 1960s, 1972 with, of all people, President Nixon creates or helps
signs the EPA into existence. The environmental movement really kind of adopted Thurow as
the poster child of environmentalism. So it's really in 1960s. So about 100 years and then
1962 was the centennial of his death. So that's really when he kind of started to become famous.
So he was just way, way, way ahead of his time. I mean, you know, I think a lot of the
concepts that he brings up really resonate today and are very important. I mean, just
the site, certainly the concept of engaging with nature, you know, put your, put your
phone away, get out of the house, see what this world has to offer. He was a big advocate
of minimalist living, getting rid of stuff. Right. Well, I think that's, that's why he
resonates so much. I mean, here it is 2024 and we're talking about this guy. I think
that when you go to high school, they all get lumped together. So you have to read Emerson,
you have to read Thurow, you have to read Moby Dick, you have to read the Scarlet Letter.
And frankly, a lot of kids that I meet, they don't really care about any of that stuff.
It's pretty glossed over. At least it wasn't my high school experience. I went to Catholic
school so we didn't read any of this stuff. I think we read Moby Dick or at least parts
of it. But anyway, so, but Thurow to a lot of younger readers and even a lot of older
readers, he seems, he seems more now. His language isn't as archaic as Emerson. It's
certainly not as archaic as somebody like Benjamin Franklin or George Washington or
any of those people from the 18th century. His works seem modern to us. And I think that's
why people are still relating and reacting to him because he's writing about stuff that
we can relate to. Like you said, you know, the minimalist thing, getting rid of stuff
and the connection with nature, especially now with the, with the green movement and
the climate change concerns. He's, he's speaking to all of that stuff in the 1850s.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I would say at least from my observation in town here, having met high
school students through the neighborhood or through some of the stuff that I do through,
through the college interview process, students are very environmentally conscious in this
town and I'm impressed by it. I mean, and socially aware. So I've been very impressed
with whatever curriculum they have going on at the high school. It's going to be a few
years before I found out my son's in kindergarten currently, but it's been, it's been pretty
impressive to meet these students. And you know, it gives me good hope for the next generations
won't, won't screw stuff up as much as ours and previous ones have.
Well, I, and you know, I do living history as thorough over at Walden Pond. So I meet
school groups from all over the country and it's a lot of the younger generation. I feel
like high school kids are way more progressive than we were when we were in high school.
I never thought about that stuff. I never was, never came across my radar.
No, same here. Same here. Plus, you know, I grew up in a Republican household,
but, but you're right. And so I meet high school and college kids and they care about the
environment. They care about black lives matter. They care about, about LGBTQ rights. I mean,
and to them it's all just natural stuff. Natural. It's not, it's not controversial.
It's not, it's, it's not what someone would call woke. It's just life.
Right. You know, it's almost like they're like, well, why, why wouldn't gay people have equal
rights? Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. So that's, that's why I'd say I've, I've been very impressed. So
uh, kudos to Cochran and it sounds like local school groups from all over the place.
Absolutely. I think that, you know, and so I think that's why Tharo really resonates with a lot of
people when, when younger people find out that he went to jail for not paying his poll tax, or if
younger people find out that he was helping people on the underground railroad, um, you know, cause
he's, let's face it, he's got kind of a bad rap for being this lone guy living in a house.
Living in a cabin by himself in Walden woods, you know, but then you say, well, no, actually he helped
run away slaves. Oh no, wait, he actually protested the Mexican war and went to jail for not paying his
poll tax. You know, when kids realize that or hear about that, they realize that there's more to this
guy than, than, than they've heard before. Yeah. No, it's interesting to me just thinking about,
um, this guy who was notorious for burying his face in the paper when he gave lectures is actually
one who was most aware of everything around him in the world. And he's not making a big thing about
it. One thing that bothered him more than anything else was somebody say an abolitionist who would do
something like hide a runaway slave or, or, or make an antislavery speech and then walk around bragging
about how he had done it. Yeah. When Tharo went to jail for not paying his poll tax, he didn't tell
anybody until like the next day. And he mentioned it to Bronson Alcott. Um, he probably mentioned it
to his family, but they were abolitionists. So they probably thought it was okay. He's not going
around making a big deal about it. It's not till three years later that, that civil disobedience
called resistance to civil government was actually published and people had to kind of push him and
say, you know, you should write about this. And he gave a lecture on it. So he's not blowing his own
horn. He's kind of letting his work and his actions speak for themselves. Yeah. Um, at a time when,
you know, we're living, he's living in a world with people like P.T. Barnum who are blowing their own
horn all the time. Yeah. And Tharo just doesn't want to be a part of that. He's going to do his
thing. Why is he going to do his thing? Because it's the right thing to do. And I think younger
people, well, that's why the counterculture was attracted to him in the 1960s and the, the beat
writers, you know, he's always been really popular with the folks who follow, follow their own drummer.
Sure. To, to coin a phrase by Henry. So yeah, so the beat writers, they see him doing his own thing.
The hippies see him doing his own thing. I first got into him back in the 80s when I was singing in
punk bands and I found a copy of civil disobedience in a punk rock record store. So, so, you know, so
it's always the, the, the, as Kerouac would say, the misfits who are, who are Indian. When I'm,
when I'm talking to a group of school kids, if I've got 50 kids in front of me and one of the kids
has, has green hair or, or a nose piercing, I can bet you a thousand dollars. Yeah, you're talking
to them. That's the kid that's going to come up to me later. Yeah. And it happens all the time.
That's fascinating. Yeah. Well, this has been incredible. You know, hopefully we can get you
back for another story down the line. Absolutely. Thank you so much for joining. I hope, I hope this
is the highlight of your career to be on season one, episode one. You know, I can retire happy now.
This is what I've always wanted to do. Awesome. Well, thank you, Richard Smith. You know, anyone
listening, where, where, where can we find you in town? I'm usually, I work a couple of days a week
over at the shop at Walden pond for the thorough society. If you want to come over and hang out
and talk about thorough, you're more than welcome to also have a Facebook page called meet Henry
David thorough. And I post stuff on there every day. I'm also the moderator for the thorough
society Facebook page. So if you want to learn more about Henry thorough than you ever thought
you would want to know, uh, check me out on Facebook. Awesome. Thank you. I appreciate it.
My pleasure. My pleasure.