Alright, this is Concord Storytellers and I am very excited for this episode.
We have with us Brianne Keith, a Concord expert and as we were talking before we started to
talk about it, it turns out we had an unknown convergence in life in the back bay as we
both went to college at the same time and lived within a block of each other.
So that's a funny coincidence.
I don't think we ran into each other during college, but here we are now in Concord and
I'm excited especially for my cousin Amy back in Michigan who is an absolute fanatic about
ghosts and all things supernatural.
Last time she visited me in Concord a couple years ago, she was excited to actually take
a ghost tour, but we didn't get to it and the next time she comes back she wants to
stay at the Colonial Inn and see if she can find anything supernatural.
So Brianne, could you please introduce yourself to our listeners?
Sure.
So I'm a writer, an author, and editor, that's my main thing, but I have been a thorough
enthusiast for years since I was 15 years old.
I turned it into a career.
I was a thorough scholar for a number of years.
I worked with this scholar named Brad Dean who was the director of the Thorough Institute
and he published some late natural history manuscripts of Thoroughs and I sort of helped
him with that in later works.
I eventually just, you know, I've been a member of the Thorough Society, I was on the board
for years and I just sort of morphed into sort of being more interested in Thorough's
relationship to spirituality.
And so I eventually became a Jyotisha, which is a Vedic astrologer, so we can talk, I'll
talk about that in a little bit.
But I also worked for public media for seven years, WGBH, Boston's public media station,
which was really fun there, and I published a book in 2017 on American Lit called American
Lit 101.
It's a trade book, so it's for the general reader, but it was kind of my love letter
to American literature.
I love it.
What inspired you to write that?
Actually somebody approached me to do that, a friend from graduate school.
She was working at a publisher and she said this would be an amazing project for you and
will you do it for me?
I know you love Thorough and all that.
So that's how that landed in my lap.
Very cool.
Yeah.
And so how did this, eventually you gave ghost tours at Inconquered?
Oh yeah, so for a while I was working for the Concord Tour Company, which was run by
my friend Alita, and I was assigned to the ghost tours.
That became another sort of avenue of interest for me.
And yeah, so I have all the lore.
Okay.
Right on.
Yep.
That's cool.
And what did you think when that was, I didn't know that was your assignment when you got
there, so that was suddenly something that you had to dive into and learn about.
And where was the information for this tour?
I can't take responsibility for it.
It was all Alita.
So she really did an amazing job.
She gave me like a 25 page guide on all of the lore that she could collect.
So I sort of just ended up studying that and that was the tour.
It was called the Ghosts in the Gloaming Tour.
Okay.
Like five or six stops.
I'm going to guess that was very popular.
Yes.
It was, especially during Halloween and all that.
Yeah.
Okay, cool.
And could you walk us through some of the highlights from the tour?
Yeah, well, we all, I feel like most people kind of, the first thing they'll think about
with ghosts in Concord is the Colonial Inn.
One of the reasons is because Ghost Hunters came, I think it was like 2010.
So the inn got put on the map because of that and they didn't find anything, by the way.
But the story with the inn is interesting.
So during the Revolutionary War, one part of the structure was owned by a doctor, Timothy,
I'm going to get his name wrong.
Yeah, Timothy Minow.
And so his home became a makeshift hospital for the soldiers.
So room 24 was his operating room and then I think room 27 was his moor.
So that's where people think, okay, that's where this is all coming from.
There's also this other story about a colonial, a colonist, sorry, a colonist, Amy White, who
was the son-in-law of Timothy.
And he supposedly went down to the battlefield, like when the battle was going on, with a
hatchet.
Huh.
And he killed one of the British soldiers that hadn't, you know, was shot, but wasn't
dead yet.
And so people did like, obviously there was a gruesome thing that happened.
So that just was a story that ended up kind of getting passed down.
So there's this, you know.
So can I ask the question then?
So there's this battle.
So is this one of those things where like, if you're a townsperson, you say, hey, there's
this battle at North Bridge and this guy went down with a hatchet and hacked this guy up.
And people are like, whoa, he kind of went a little too far with that.
Yeah.
So it's like, okay, okay.
So that wasn't like, this was just part of the battle.
This was, okay, this guy was, that's a little too intense for what this was.
Exactly.
Okay.
So yeah, it's just, and so he just remained, his name remains imprinted in people's memories
for that.
But he, I guess there's a story that there's a red coat that appears at the bar at the
Colonial Inn asking for a drink.
And so people think it's the guy that got hacked by Ami White.
But I think that the biggest story is that there was a young couple that stayed there
on their honeymoon.
I think it was 1966.
And the bride ended up writing a letter to the innkeeper and saying, hey, you know, I
was there.
I was, you know, I had this experience in room 24 where there was a gray shadowy figure
at the end of my bed and then it disappeared.
And so that was like the first kind of like, you know, documented.
Yeah.
Gotcha.
Interesting.
So we're definitely kind of testing my limits here.
I'm going to tell you, I have to confess that when I was younger, growing up in Tennessee,
there was this legend of the bell witch.
I don't know if you've heard of this pretty similar story about a family and someone kind
of went a little too far and started killing members of their own family.
And there's this legend of the bell witch that if you say, I don't believe in the bell
witch five times in a row at midnight, that she'll appear and like scratch you or something.
It was terrifying to me as a kid.
And we went, I went with some friends very stupidly to the site of the bell witch house
late at night around Halloween one year.
And I just got the spooks, the hair standing up on my arms.
I think that's might've might've been what caused me to retreat into science fields later
in life to to sort of say, okay, let me like analytically try to prove that none of this
is real to me.
But I also think that if I go to the Colonial Inn now, now that I know about room 27 and
about this British soldier that I'm going to probably watch my back a little bit more
than I have in the past when I go in there.
Just because in the back of my mind, there's this this experience I had when I was younger.
I really feel like when I hear these stories, then I visit these places, it starts to literally
haunt me when I go there.
Yeah.
How old were you again?
I must have been 14.
I was with my older sister and that crew.
So very impressionable and a little naive.
And yeah, it didn't go well for me.
I also can't watch scary movies anymore because of the movie.
Remember the miniseries with Tim Curry?
Yeah.
So I thought I was cool with scary movies.
I wasn't cool with scary movies.
I haven't watched one since I was like 15.
Yeah.
My aunt used to take me and my cousins.
You know, she used to have us over for sleepovers.
And she's like a youngish aunt.
So she would show us the Freddy Krueger movies and then I would come home horrified.
My mother is so upset.
The cool aunt.
Oh no.
Devastating.
Yeah, I won't forget it.
And you said, I know you said that Ghost Hunters came in 2010.
So I haven't seen that episode.
Like what were they, what were they doing there to try to find, you said, try to find
something?
You know, I went in this rabbit hole of these Ghost Hunters shows because I use them sometimes
as like background noise or these like, you know, shows that have a similar thing every
time.
And usually they go in and it's that electromagnetic meter.
Okay.
And sometimes they can catch voices.
So I think it's that tool, but they're just looking for like changes in that, you know,
the magnetic.
I'm not a scientist, but they're looking for anomalies and sometimes they'll catch them
sometime.
And then they use photographs, they have special cameras.
And so, you know, sometimes they will pick up something like they definitely I've seen
shows where they have picked up shapes or like cloudy figures.
They're either like black or gray or some form of like, you know, like kind of a hazy
specter kind of thing.
Yeah, sometimes they'll move but but there was enough and maybe they caught some sound.
I don't really remember that episode.
But I know the end result was like, for all intents and purposes.
Okay, right on.
Cool.
Yeah.
And then I know I think you mentioned the Old Manse was another place that.
Yeah, the Old Manse is so interesting to me.
This that so that house, Nathaniel, the ghost story associated with that is that Nathaniel
Hawthorne lived there with his wife.
And supposedly there were two sort of things that were happening there.
And I was her Ripley, who was a met Concord minister that had lived there right before
Hawthorne.
Basically, Hawthorne said that he could sense that he could feel his silk robes going through
the hallways, you know, pass by him and he could hear his voice and things like that.
And they also heard the noise of servants, like coffee grinding and I forget the other
sounds they heard, you know, just like work that ironing was the other one.
And then they'd wake up and none of that work was done.
So they kind of thought, OK, this is like the sounds of servants who have lived here
before.
And they were coming from the attic.
So the sounds are coming from the attic.
But, you know, Nathaniel Hawthorne was a very dreamy guy, like, you'd want to believe like
he is a supernatural, like he would believe in that.
Yeah.
So well, that's interesting, though, because I mean, I think to me, I was thinking, OK,
well, if you hear some boards creaking or something else that you could explain with
the wind like that, that's one thing.
But if you're hearing more like coffee grinding is a different sound that's not happening
from the right.
One of the things I just want to say, like I had this sort of close friend 10, 15 years
ago, his father was an anthropologist and he did a lot of work in Italy.
And my friend said that he was working in the basement of these Roman churches and he
saw which he, you know, on more than one occasion, this line of men walking and they'd be in
rags.
And he ended up sort of coming up with the idea that these were actually Roman slaves
and they were coming in the Appian way, which was like one of the major roads into Rome
that this church was like built on or near something like that.
But his theory and I think this is like something that's shared with anthropologists.
You know, one of the theories is that when there's an event that happens in life, like
he did my friend described as like if I murdered you right now, like that was his example.
He's like this would leave a mark on this actual space.
And so you're seeing like this imprint of an event on the space.
So that I've always sort of like held that in my mind of like, okay, it's a theory, whatever.
But like maybe you're hearing remnants of something that was, you know, happened that
had some import to it.
Or makes sense.
So that's that's the story with that house.
But you know, it does that house is also interesting to me because of the ley line thing, which
I know you're going to talk about.
Yeah, you know, I'm interested to hear about that.
I think that was a whole new subject for me.
I think there was was there one more the the John Ball house.
Yes, so the John Ball house, that's now the Concord Art Association.
That's on Lexington Road.
Okay.
Right outside the rotary of the yellow house.
So that house was dates back to 1761.
And the founder of the Concord Art Association was a woman named Elizabeth Wentworth Higgins.
She moved there in 1923.
And so she the story is that she was depressed and she ended up hanging herself in the house.
And people that, you know, been in the house report a lot of coldness, like these cold
breezes that go by them.
And it was the house is interesting, too, because it supposedly was was one of the stops
on the Underground Railroad, which was discovered when they did renovation.
I forget what year it was in 1922.
And they found a secret chamber with like, you know, cannonballs and odd things from
from that century.
So the other thing that is interesting about that house is people reported feeling coldness
going in and out of the front doorway.
Okay.
And then they did more renovations and they discovered a skeleton underneath.
Oh, wow.
Yeah, the doorway.
Interesting.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, that's pretty chill.
Yeah.
Wait, wait.
So now that they've so I'm assuming they removed the skeleton when they did the revisions.
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah.
Do we still feel like the chilly breezes there or is it just like it's mostly out of there
now?
Well, I don't know.
I mean, I know Alita said people that are there now, like, don't want to talk about
it.
Yeah.
They're just like, they're like, yeah, maybe.
But we don't want to.
Yeah.
Well, yeah.
Well, maybe if, yeah, maybe like setting up a create like a good creative space on top
of it, something that culturally significant.
Maybe that can kind of just neutralize that a little bit and chill out the haunting effects.
And now that there's something good and community productive going on there.
Yeah.
So maybe that's hopefully that's something that because I'm a little bit I want to be
able to go there in the future.
You're never going to forget this.
No, yeah.
Basically.
Yeah.
Okay.
Season.
Yeah.
This is episode two.
I'm moving now.
Cool.
Well, I really wanted to talk about lay lines because I looked into these a little bit and
I think you touched on this a little bit with this idea of it, by the way, to say if I merge
you right now, that would leave a question that would leave an impression on me as well
and make me think about that concept for a while.
So it sounded like that.
That sort of concept is what plays into this lay line theory.
So can you just educate me on this?
Yeah.
Like, you know, I started hearing about them when I was doing tours.
So when I was like, you know, more like hobnobbing with the residents here and this and that
and the other tour guides, it just started being like this thing that would you hear
about.
I was like, what's lay lines?
And so, you know, I mean, all types of people, you know, just would say, oh, it's it's basically
there's a lay line that runs through the old man's in the old north bridge.
So I ended up kind of doing a little research on on them.
And I know that the, you know, the sort of the term lay line was coined by an amateur
archaeologist named Alfred Watkins.
He was looking at a map of all these ancient sites and was standing on a hill, like looking
at that map and he noticed that they were all on a straight line.
And so he said he had this like rush of insight that, you know, ancient peoples were like
building on some invisible line, maybe possibly.
But he like I did a little extra research on this and he, you know, he wrote a book
on this and he basically said, oh, they were just like, you know, trade routes that they
weren't, you know, there was nothing sort of mythical about them.
I don't think he was like sort of responsible for the mythical or supernatural, I guess
you could say, sort of interpretation of them.
But his idea that they were trade routes kind of got squashed, like because it didn't make
sense.
So I know in the 60s, other people kind of took up the idea, but it kind of resonated
with ideas that were already being like passed down, that ancient people were building spiritual
sites on energetic areas.
That the, you know, that there are certain areas on earth that have this, what are some
of the terms, rivers of supernatural energy.
Okay.
So it's like these invisible rivers of supernatural energy.
The more I read about them or kind of like thought about them and the more of like my
own experiences with meditation or, you know, learning the Vedas and all this, is that they
might just, you know, if we go with this, right?
Right.
Yeah.
If we go, they might just be these areas where the other side is just more the veil, you
know, the, the, between that Austin, the other side here and the other side, it's just thin.
And so it's like, you know, these energies come in and out and it could be, I think they're
similar to the fairy paths in Ireland.
Okay.
And you'll, if you do like a YouTube search, you'll see a lot of, you know, these Irish
farmers being like, oh, that's the fairy path.
And the story is about how that's where they live.
We don't, we don't, you know, bother them.
And, you know, if you, if you kind of stay in those areas, they'll come and kind of just
play with you.
So that's, that's kind of another thing that's related, you know?
Yeah.
Do you have, have you noticed any, I'm just curious.
And the question that I had just now, is there, have you noticed any ties to like, maybe it's
a higher or lower elevation within a certain area or near a water source?
I know you had said sort of these like not physical rivers, but spiritual rivers were
just a, maybe a particularly peaceful place to be, or is there been any sort of geological
connection you found there, or is it purely just like, these people just felt like this
was the, it just felt like the right place, just purely spiritually?
You know, I was like, like I found an article on life science, like people had gone and
taken meters to magnet, magnetometers, found nothing.
Like, you know, they're, they're debunked that way.
Yeah.
But they're, but then you'll see other people like with dousing rods and, and they go crazy
and those dousing rods are strange.
You know, I'm not sure how I feel about them, but they, you know, they, so you'll see that
happen, right?
And so, but no, I, I didn't see, I haven't seen like that, you know, these areas are
near water.
In fact, there's supposedly another ley line runs through Shelburne falls in Western Mass,
which happens to be the site of a Vipassana meditation center.
Okay.
So that's kind of interesting, like why they are.
Right.
And there's a, I just talked to my friend last night because he was talking about doing
this today and he's an acupuncturist in Rockport.
And he said, oh yeah, there's a ley line through Halibut state park and people from China come
to do Tai Chi there.
Oh, no way.
Yeah.
So it's kind of like this word of mouth.
But it's fascinating.
Yeah.
You know, and then the thing that I think is interesting about the old man's and then old
North bridge is like, these were really the sites of like this, I think they were highly
energetic sites in terms of like having historical significance and, and you know, ushering in
a revolutionary change.
Yeah.
I mean, and the butterfly effect is our world today is significantly defined by things that
happen there.
Yeah.
That's cool.
And when I think about the role for Reverend Emerson, he, he, I think that Reverend William
Emerson, who's the grandfather of Ralph Waldo Emerson.
And when I think about him, sort of, you know, he was the, the conquered, he was conquered
town minister, like this figurehead and he sanctioned the war, which I think was that
really radical thing to do to say, you know, here's this man of the cloth and he's saying,
yeah, you should fight.
Yeah.
So I think that's, it's like, I just think of him in that house, like kind of like saying
that and he was, he watched the fight.
He watched the shot heard around the world, like from his lawn.
Yeah.
I mean, yeah.
So for anybody who hasn't been to North bridge and old man's these, and we talk about these
as two separate historical places and conquered, but they are within a hundred yards.
Yeah.
So if you, if you go visit the North bridge to see where the shots were fired, as you're
approaching North bridge from monument street, look to your left, old man says right there.
So if you were just making breakfast in the kitchen there, you looked out, you would see
this battle happening.
I mean, how would you know that it would spark what it sparked, but it, it was right there.
So it was a place for these people to observe it.
Yeah.
It's very famous for it.
Yep.
So yeah, I, I just, I don't know.
It's just an interesting thing.
It's part of conquered lore for sure.
Yep.
People will, even if you just walked around today and they'd be like, yeah, I'm sure you'd
see, meet somebody and say, of course, you know.
So, so I mean, does that make it so for people who follow lay lines, I mean, you mentioned
Western Massachusetts, people will travel there to do Tai Chi.
Does that make so conquered obviously a historical destination, but also is this a spiritual
destination for people?
Yeah.
And how, and how might we observe that?
If I go to old man's North bridge, might I see people like in groups doing Tai Chi or
meditation or something like that?
I think you, yeah, you might see that.
I think you see that more often at the pond.
Okay.
Which probably Richard was just asking me this, this morning, my friend, he was asking
me, is that the same way line that goes through pot while in pond?
Because you know, he, he's, he has heard that there's one that goes through there.
So I think so.
Okay.
We looked at a map, you'd probably see the line goes straight through them.
So you know, and we obviously know thorough treated that place as, you know, a secret
place.
So, um, uh, yeah, so that's cool.
Yeah.
That's really interesting.
Thank you for sharing.
Um, I'm gonna look into this more.
Yeah.
Um, let's take a quick break.
And then I wanted to talk about Vedic astrology.
Did I say it correctly?
Okay.
We are back to discuss Vedic astrology.
And the reason we took the break is, um, we are going to do a live reading for me and
that involves some personal details that I didn't want to release to anyone listening.
Um, so I'm excited to hear this and a little nervous, but, um, tell me what we got here.
Yeah.
Right.
So I'll just preface what, what is, what is this?
What is Vedic astrology?
So I'll even step a little bit back.
Like, you know, I obviously, you know, heavily involved in thorough and all his writings.
Um, eventually, you know, at the first, I was sort of more interested in his, uh, social
commentary.
It morphed kind of when I was like late twenties into, um, more spiritual, you know, his, his
spirituality, you know, me sort of thinking heavily about, you know, deeply about that
and really being like attracted to his, uh, you know, relationship to the Vedas, which
is the ancient, um, Hindu scriptures, um, and really realizing that that was like the
fountainhead of a lot of what the transcendentalists were doing and thinking.
And so that just ended up morphing into me becoming, um, a Vedic astrologer.
It's a long windy path, but short, short, short and sweet.
The Vedic astrology is a branch of the Vedas.
It's basically one of the six Angas, which are limbs.
So the Vedas are, you know, these scriptures and then they have these explanatory limbs
and Jyotish, which is, uh, Vedic astrology is one of those limbs.
So it explains the astronomy and astrology of, you know, the cosmos, um, through, through
the Vedanta, through this, this philosophical principle.
So you know, we know astrology here in the West from a totally different vantage point,
you know, the Western astrology uses a different zodiac and, um, you know, this astrology
was really preserved in India, um, as well as it could be.
So there's a lot of things that are different.
So one thing that, um, people notice right away is their sun sign will be not what they,
you know, not what it is in the Western, uh, system.
So that's because, uh, Vedic astrology is using a stellar based zodiac, um, and it's
astronomically precise.
Okay.
So the sun sign that I'll tell you that you are is, is actually like an astronomically
precise sun.
Okay.
So if I'm hearing that correctly, I've always known myself to be a Virgo.
Yeah.
That, how was that measured then from the Western viewpoint?
So basically there's, there's something called the precession of the equinoxes.
So the earth's tilt in relation to the sky changes a little bit over years.
Vedic astrology, the sidereal zodiac takes that into account.
Okay.
Western tropical zodiac does not.
So all the signs right now have a 24 degree difference.
So some people will actually be the same sun sign that they are.
And you know, in what the Western zodiac astrology that they are and, um, in the Vedic, but,
but most people are pushed back as science.
So your sun sign is Leo.
Oh, all right.
Yes.
So you're Leo.
Okay.
I like this.
I've kind of always wanted to be a Leo.
All right.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
We're starting off.
We're starting off good here.
All right.
So yeah, you're, I'm going to pull up, uh, your chart.
Um, so you're, you're, you're, you're, you're, you're, you're, you're, you're, you're, you're,
you're, you're, you're, you're little birds on the ì°.
So, so the first fit, you know, the other thing about this is we're looking at your
karma.
So you have to kind of go, go with us just for this time, whether you believe in, you
know, you get the soul reincarnates or not.
That, that's what this is based on this, that you have reincarnated.
Okay.
You have certain desires that compelled you to come back.
They're really looking at those desires.
Okay.
Hold you back.
Um, and the map of, you know, there's there, uh, we read the maps.
map of them. And so, so if we look at your chart right away, actually I'm gonna hold
this down. So you are a Gemini ascendant. Okay. Okay. You and I actually share an ascendant,
so I can speak a lot about this. Okay. And you, within Vedic astrology there are these
little star clusters, so we look at the signs and we break them down into tiny subdivisions
called nakshatras, where there are these star clusters. They have a lot of meaning and actually
they are responsible for sort of initiating the karmic unfolding of your life. Okay. So
they're super important. So you're, the nakshatra that is at the top of your chart, your lagna,
is Arjuna. And I share this as well. Okay. So we have a lot of similarities. So Arjuna
is the symbol for Arjuna is a human head. Okay. It's a very mental nakshatra. So Einstein
also had this. Okay. Right? Just a person that is constantly thinking. Like they're
ahead. Like take, we don't even need a body. We could just like be ahead and thinking all
the time would be great. Prone to overthinking maybe? Yes, prone to overthinking, all that
stuff. Okay. So, so sorry, this is, this is what you were saying, this is what brought
me back. So this is like my natural state, my, my nature versus even my nurture. My nature
is overthinking. Okay. That's spot on. Yep. Yep. So, and, and really Arjuna is a very
destructive nakshatra. I will say that. Oh good. Yeah. So we want to, the impulse for
that, that nakshatra is to destroy anything that's not true. Okay. After truth. And actually
I of course looked up the Rose, the Rose chart and he has Arjuna prominent too. Oh nice.
Okay. So I could go on about that, but I'll, well let's, let's go over a little bit more
things, you know, things that are popping out here. So you have moon at the top of your
chart as well. Okay. So the moon is the mind. Okay. And so now if you have the moon at the
top of your chart, which correlates physically to your physical head. Okay. Your mind is
always on. Like your mind is very present in your head. And you're that nakshatra that
your, your moon is in is called Marigashira. And the symbol for a Marigashira is an antelope's
head. Okay. And the sort of mythology behind that is it's a seeker. Okay. So, you know,
like, like think of a deer, you know, just constantly running in the forest, like that
energy. So the mind is constantly seeking, seeking, you know, definitely a person that
would have many hobbies. So someone, so someone per se maybe used to be into engineering business
now is doing podcasting in a small town in Massachusetts. Okay. All right. All right.
All right. Okay. We're still on. We're still on. Yep. Okay. So now we take up tour to,
you know, and on the chart, we'll go to the second house. So you have Venus, Rahul, love
this. Okay. So, so Rahul is the north node of the moon. So Rahul is actually like your
destiny point. It's, it's wherever it is in a chart is saying, okay, this is where you're
going. Okay. This is like your chief impulse, your chief desire. So what is the second house
with, with Rahul there? Second house is speech. Okay. So it correlates, correlates physically
to the mouth. So like what we put in and out of the mouth. So if you have Rahul in the
second house, Rahul is also like endless cravings and desires, cause it's really pushing you.
It's it's fueling your drives and your desires and this, this incarnation. So you have that
drive and desire in the field of speech. Okay. You want to speak. Okay. You want to speak.
And so, and you have Venus next to Rahul. So Venus is going to give you pleasant speech.
Oh, okay. It's, you know, Venus is the planet of charm and grace and beauty and art. And
I know one of my teachers said, anytime you see somebody with Venus, Rahul, like what,
if they go into the arts, they'll flourish. Okay. So I'm giving you another career. Okay.
So interesting. So someone driven to speak, but also speak pleasantly and charmingly.
So I'll say that typically in my life, I've always been diplomatic. Like if I'm in a group
setting and there's an argument going on, my, my role tends to be to mediate, hear everyone's
everyone's thoughts, organize them and reach a group conclusion. I'm not someone who, I'm
not someone who will latch onto a point and just say, I must now win this argument. It's,
I've always been a diplomat. So is that, does that kind of jive with that?
Yeah. Venus is the planet of diplomacy. Okay. All right. It's a, it owns the sign Libra,
which is the scales, which is like, you know, interpersonal relationships. It's smooths
those, those, those kinds of, it's smooths relationships. Okay. It wants to create relationships.
Now your Venus is in the sign cancer. So there's a sort of nurturing aspect to that Venus,
the Rahu as well. Okay. Just looking what nakshatra is. So puna varsu is what your Venus
is in and the Rahu is in Ashlesha. So I'll say that Ashlesha is going to dominate that.
Okay. So Ashlesha is the symbol is a snake. And so Ashlesha energy is kind of like a snake
charm or energy. Oh no. It wants to mesmerize because it wants to sort of, it wants to kind
of raise the Kundalini and other people. If the Kundalini is the energy that goes up and
down the spine. Okay. So if you think of like the snake charmer, sort of making the snake
go up, like that's kind of physically what the Ashlesha energy wants to do to another
person. Okay. Is make them alive. So this speech that you have, like I think it's like
you actually want to sort of raise, let's say you want to raise consciousness with your
speech. Okay. Like it's not just, yes it's diplomatic, but you also kind of want to push
the needle forward a little bit. Yeah. Yeah. I'd say that's fair. At first when you were
describing that, I was like, wait a minute, am I like a snake charmer, snake oil salesman?
No. I wouldn't, as I wouldn't drive, but no, I get it. Yeah. No, that's, I would say that's
true. I like people to reach understanding, to continue to evolve as people, to continue
to learn new things. So, okay. We're still, we're still on. We're still on. So then you
have a packed third house. So you have sun and Mercury and Jupiter and your third house
is in the sign of Leo. So sorry, the first house was my nature. The second house was
my destination. What's the third house? Yeah. The third house and the second house is only
your destination just cause Rahoo's there. Okay. Oh, okay. So second house just in general
has to do with speech. Okay. Gotcha. And also your early life, it looks like your early
life was a little bit unusual. It could have had some unusual elements in there just because
Rahoo's there and Rahoo's unusual. So, yeah. Okay. Yeah. I won't dive too deep into that,
but yes, that's true. So, and it left a mark on you is really what the chart's showing.
So the sun, Mercury and Jupiter, that's okay. So the third house you're asking is about
communication. Okay. But more in the sense of like ideas. So second house is like just,
you know, speech. Yep. Like, but third house is like, what ideas am I communicating? Um,
and you've got three planets there. So there's a lot of energy in terms of like, I want to
communicate. Okay. Um, the sun is, you have a great sun. It's in, uh, it's in this nakshatra,
uh, poor Vipalguni. Okay. This, this energy of poor Vipalguni, uh, it's the, it's a lion,
lion type energy as all the Leo, but the symbol is kind of the main of the lion. So you'll
see poor Vipalguni strong and like Mick Jagger Madonna. Oh wow. Okay. Right. Like the performer.
Okay. Like, like it's all like it's, it's a, it's a pooba nakshatra meaning luxury.
Like, like there's a real desire to sort of have luxury, but also just present that. So
it'd be like, have fun, you know, like think of Mick Jagger on the stage. Like he's so
energetic. He's such a, you know, wild figure. Like that's poor Vipalguni. So like some,
so would that fit into, I'm someone who I don't need luxury, um, in my life. Um, that's
my point to the indoor sauna right behind me in my base, in my basement recording studio.
Um, but when I do indulge in something, I like to share it with my friends and my family.
Um, I won't, I won't necessarily do something luxurious for myself. I will, I will want to
share it. And that's absolutely true. Yep. Yep. Like there's, and you should, I mean,
this is like what you, this is why you came back is to experience luxury, you know, like
that's, you want to sort of, there's no like judgment on, you know, it's like this system
really allows you or like teaches you to just not have any judgment on people's like, you
know, there's a desire they had to, when they came back, they want to experience that. So,
um, the sun is next to Mercury and this is, this makes for an intellectual lifetime. Okay.
Cause Mercury's, uh, you know, the planet of the intellect, different than the mind.
So there's a definite distinction within the Vedas even that the, of the Mercury and of
the mind being, you know, there's different natures of mind. Okay. Um, so the Mercury
is like the, the, the sort of impulse to sort of categorize things and make distinctions
and you know, measure things like the, it's a science, it's the intellect or scientific
mind. So you've got that, you know, you've got Mercury next to suns, you know, so sun
is sort of like infusing that Mercury, that intellectual, that intellect with its energy.
So it makes for a very, um, like I said, just an intelligent, very intelligent, but also
intellectual lifetime. So it's also Mercury is also important for the planet. Okay. Wow.
Well, that's interesting. I, I'm not going to speak to whether or not I'm an intelligent
person. I do get made fun of for all the spreadsheets I make. Right? I have a spreadsheet for pretty
much everything. Yeah. You also have, you have, um, you have three planets in poor Rufa'l
Gouni. Is that odd or rare? It is a little odd. Okay. It's a little rare to have them.
Oh gosh. You have something called a planetary war. I just picked up. Okay. So Mercury and
Jupiter are at the same degree in your chart. Very interesting. Okay. So, so when the planets
are at the same degree, it's called a Graha Yudha. So it's a planetary war. So those,
those, the rays of those planets are intermingled. So there could be a struggle between the two
energies. What's, what are the two energies? Mercury wants to say, Mercury is more like
morally neutral and sort of just wants to say, these are the facts and this is like
the information, right? Jupiter said, no, I, I want to, I want to have wisdom, you know,
like I want to understand the wisdom behind this. You know, there's a higher sort of moral
principle. So there could be a push and pull between that. Okay. You know, like here's
what my intellect says. Here's what my higher mind says. That's more, you know, um, you
know, for you, the Jupiter rules, the seventh house and the 10th house. So this could come
out in, um, this could actually come out. Your mother could be involved in this, um,
because she's represented by Mercury in your chart. Okay. And so she could kind of, you
know, she could butt heads with maybe, um, your partner or, or your, or somebody in your
workplace. This doesn't always have to be that, but, um, but I will say your mother
looks interesting in this chart because she, first of all, she's sitting at the top of
your chart. She's the moon. So she's right on your head all the time. Okay. Well, we're
still, we're still pretty spot on. All I'm hearing, what I'm thinking is I'm thinking,
maybe this is the source of any anxiety in my life. Yeah. I don't know that like someone
who I get from, from the birth, I guess, who's an overthinker, but then also has a conflict
between like, I guess, like the factual choice and the higher sort of the higher moral choice.
Yeah. I get stuck a lot. Yeah. I get stuck a lot when I'm making choices sometimes. Yeah.
That makes sense. Yeah. And, and, but you know, you have the, the, the mother influences
strong when you see that in the first house. So like, I think that, you know, that's influencing
your mind as well. So, um, but this is a very intellectual chart. I mean, this is, this
is an intelligent person. Wow. Is that, is that rare also? Or is that, yeah, like you
don't always see, okay. See prominent third house moon at the top, Gemini, Ardress, and
then all those things that I mentioned. Okay. So interesting. I mean, yeah, again, I won't,
I'm not going to speak to whether I'm intelligent. People will argue that I've heard, I've heard
both sides of that coin for me. I will say like, so there's another interesting part
of this system, which is the timing of your life. Okay. So these maharishas, um, you're
in a Saturn maharisha. So you've been in one since 2015. So you might've noticed that year
being, um, you know, memorable for some reason, because you shifted into like a new period,
the Saturn periods, 19 years. Um, and you were previously in a Jupiter period from 18
to 34. So those years were really marked by, you know, you know, you're out looking for
information, like you're, you're seeking information, you're learning all that stuff. But Saturn
here is in the fourth house. So this is more about home. There's an emphasis on home. Um,
you know, even thinking about home, you know, your home place, but establishing a home and
all that stuff. Um, so you're building, these are kind of building yards. Yeah. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah. That's spot on. Um, well, let me, let me skip to the, the, the, the anxious part
for me. What's in my future. Yeah. What's in your future? Um, let me see where you are
right now. You're in a, uh, you're in a Saturn Venus period. So interestingly enough, you
know, we were saying the Venus Rahu is making you, you have desire for speaking. And so
since 2021, you've kind of that, that area, right, has gotten highlighted. So this sort
of the podcasting or whatever, like maybe you started germinating around then, um, but
you're going to really hit a stride. You're in the middle of it and you'll get, uh, the
end of it is February of 2025. Wow. Right. When this was sort of, it's going to wrap
up. Interesting. No, that is interesting. I mean, just from, from my point of view,
um, the way my life has evolved, um, you know, I was an engineer, I was in engineering and
business for, I call it phase one of my career. Um, we're almost starting a therapy session
now. No, no, it's cool. I think we should, we should air it. I think this, I think that
hearing someone have insight into this could then maybe someone listens and says, Hey,
maybe you want to try this out to see if I can organize thoughts about my own life. But
when I was in engineering and business, I think, you know, I was really tapping into
my desire to create things, build things, make things that help the world. But when
you're a builder, you tend to be more of a back room person. You're not, you're spending
all of your time doing that. You're not out like talking, interacting with people as much,
which I really enjoy as well. Um, so I think that when I, when I stopped working in engineering
and business worlds, I took me a couple of years to figure out what I wanted to do with
my life next as sort of a next career or next major hobby, whatever this might end up being
and doing something like this, where I'm actually talking and speaking to people, being out
the more of the Mick Jagger role of being out front and center and sharing stories with
people became very attractive to me, not just because it's something I've always liked doing,
but it was kind of something I missed out on during that first phase of my career where
it was necessary for me to be in a different role. Um, so wow, that's cool. And by the
way, Venus also rules math. Okay. So it's not just art. It's also like, it gives art,
you know, if you have a Venus, Rahul, it's also going to give you mathematical aptitude.
Okay. So it's just, you can choose, right? So you're just, you're like, Hey, you get
three planets in the third house of communication and a very showy nakshatra. You want to get
out there and you actually want to, like I said, that Venus Rahul, you want to rate in
the Ashley and you know, Rahul and that you want to raise people's consciousness. That's
really kind of the angle. You know, when you get out in February of next year, that's when
you get into your son sub period. When you get into these sun sub sub periods, their
career making there, it's like when you're more visible in the world. Okay. So you can
expect, you know, you have a good year next year where you'll be more notice. Okay. All
right. We'll see. We'll have to revisit in March and see what, see what, see where we
are. Exactly. We will revisit. Cool. Well, this has been, this has been awesome. I can't
tell you how much I appreciate you coming. Um, and I just, it's incredible. The career
you've had with such a broad range of interests. And I can imagine that as a writer and creative
artist that having this just wealth and breadth of interests and historical backgrounds has
been led to like a really fun career for you. Yeah, it really has. I'm a little bit of an
oddball, but I'm happy for it. We like that in Concord, Massachusetts. Right. So yeah,
thank you so much. Thank you. Um, and yeah, I'd love to have you back again sometime too
to chat. Thanks, Brianne.