Okay, this is Conquered Storytellers, episode three, with a very, very, very special guest.
The 2022 Templeton Prize award winner, 2005 King Faisal Prize winner, 2004 Nobel Prize winner.
This is kind of like when Tiger Woods tees off at a golf tournament and they list all the
all the tournaments he's won. Concord Resident, Neighbor, and full disclosure, my father-in-law.
So if this goes poorly, then we can we could have him meet the parents part three premise, I guess.
Welcome. Thank you. Thanks for coming on. Yeah. Also happy birthday. It's coming up. I guess it's
your birthday week. We celebrated yesterday and I'd say I like really like shopping for presents
for you, right? Because these days I get to go to the toy section at Target with my son and pick out
fun stuff to play with. I'll say that it's interesting. We've known each other for a long
time now, but we don't we haven't really talked a lot about work stuff in either in either of our
lives. I think we kind of know if a day went well at work or not. But I'll say one of the highlights
from my business career was guest lecturing at your class, the Cross MIT and Arizona State class.
Because I thought it was a cool way to give insight into the things I've been doing for the
previous decade. And you got to I think see maybe a little more than you had seen in the past
of the work I had done. I've gotten a lot of peaks on it. Yeah. So I think I'm excited to talk to you
about the work you've done currently, but also in the past. And I think it's worth asking how many
how many jobs do you currently have? It depends how you count. But I, I would, I think I have four affiliations.
MIT, Arizona State University. I'm also a professor there and Stockholm University.
And then I have a relation some relationships in China. There's something called the T.D. Lee
Institute of which I was director and now I'm chief scientist. And then there's something called
the Wilczek Quantum Center. Both are in Shanghai and there I'm also chief scientist and
sort of invested because my name is on it. Yeah. And that's is that fully built now and functioning?
It's growing. It's evolving, I would say. Yes. So it's neither one is a finished product, but they
they've come a long way and are starting to be significant institutions in the scientific
firmament. That's great. I wanted to I think that for the perspective of this project I've been doing,
I don't think we'll go super deep into theoretical physics, but I wanted this kind of
talk a bit about how your career got going and how it's evolved, how it evolved over time.
I think that for most people in the world, something like a Templeton Prize or a Nobel Prize is
kind of like not real. It's something like almost unattainable and something that doesn't happen to
people in their world. Just getting started, how did you get interested in science in the first place?
Well, I've always been interested in science. My earliest memories are of taking things apart
and putting them back together. And I had a little notebook where I tried to make big numbers
and I saved up money to buy a telescope. All this happened in early childhood. So it came naturally.
Also, my parents very much encouraged it and my school very much encouraged it.
And the outside world very much encouraged it at the time. I was born in 1951, so formative years
were in New York City during the Cold War. And the whole country was kind of mobilized by
this feeling that we needed to have technology that was going to protect us. And there was still
cultural memory fresh from World War II when the atom bomb and scientists were kind of like
magicians, very powerful, very central to the country's flourishing. And we were necessary to
stand up to threats, perceived threats. It was the time of the space war, the time of the
threats. It was the time of the space race and Sputnik.
So it was an exciting time. And so it was growing up with being a scientist was a very aspirational
occupation, it sounds like, even certainly more so than today.
I think so, yes. It was much more viewed as a crucial component of society flourishing.
And scientists, as I said, there was still the penumbra of the atom bomb and this kind of magic,
that enormous power that scientists had. It was like magicians, but for real.
Well, I remember, do you remember looking, you were looking in your parents basement and
you had this, it was almost like a Cuban Missile Crisis board game. Do you remember finding that?
Well, yeah. I had many toys that touched on these themes.
That's wild.
But yes, this and I had a set of model rockets of different sizes and shapes. So it was sort of
showed our arsenal, different things like that. And I really enjoyed those things too, I have to say.
Yeah. And when specifically, you were always into sort of general sciences and math,
when specifically did you decide that physics was your passion?
Oh, I didn't decide on physics till quite late. In fact, when I went to college at the University
of Chicago, my intention was to try to understand how minds work rigorously with mathematical
methods. So what would now be called computer science, but also mathematical logic and
philosophy was a mixture of all those things. That's what I thought I would do. But when I
learn more about it, I realized that it was premature, that there just wasn't enough
basis to do what I hoped to do. And so I majored in math just to keep my options open.
And then I went to Princeton as a graduate student. I was still pretty young when I went to
Princeton. I had raced through school. And I went to graduate school in Princeton as a math graduate
student. It was kind of under false pretenses. I was pretty sure I didn't want to do pure mathematics.
But it was kind of the path of least resistance because it was easy to fulfill the requirements.
And I was pretty good at it. So I did that. And I looked around when I got to Princeton. I was
really kind of in the wilderness. I didn't know what I wanted to do. As I learned more about pure
mathematics, I became more certain about what I didn't want to do, which was that. But I went to
the seminars about physics, about biology, about computers. Although there wasn't so much about
computers at that time. Then... Were you even using... I mean, there was no computer science,
you said, but I mean, people were using, just starting to use computers around that time.
Well, it was the IBM 360. So it was a gigantic room that had access to this machine,
you know, with tapes spinning around and flashing lights. But to actually use it, you had punch cards.
You would type in a side room, you would type in these punch cards and feed them into the computer.
And you wouldn't get immediate output. You'd have to wait 20 minutes and then you'd get error
messages saying, oh, this, your semicolons and... They wouldn't get useful error messages, actually,
but things wouldn't work. And then you dope it out and figure out that the semicolon was in the
wrong column or something like that. And then when finally you got things to work, the output was in
a completely different building. It was a different world.
So it was a different world. So that actually impacted some calculations I was trying to do
later. But yeah, it was a different world. Anyway, it just so happened... Well, by kind of shopping
around and seeing what was going on, I got the impression that very interesting things were
happening in physics at that time that used the kind of mathematics that I really liked.
When I was a senior at the University of Chicago, or my last year at the University of Chicago,
I had taken a course from a professor named Peter Freund about symmetry in physics or group theory
as applied to physics that I really, really, really super enjoyed. He was very charismatic,
very enthusiastic. And it was the mathematics that I really liked. I fell in love with the quantum
theory of angular momentum, which to this day is my favorite thing in physics. It's this amazing
mapping of mathematically ideal structures into the physical world where you can make based on
very compelling kind of ideal mathematical conceptions, do calculations that then you
compare with experiments that very concrete things about the directions that particles emerge from
the decays and things like that. And not vague, it's very specific in details. I really liked that.
But I didn't... And he also gave the impression that there were still open questions. There were
lots of loose ends. But still, I didn't make up my mind at that point. Just logistically,
it was not a trivial thing to change programs in graduate school.
Well, especially in graduate school because professors only have so many slots for people.
When you go to graduate school as a mathematician, you're expected to be a mathematician.
But I was very responsible and kind of naive at that time. I didn't realize that that was
the expectation. Well, you were really young too though. I was very young. Were you 18 or 19
when you got out there? Yeah, I just turned 18. Just turned 18 to start the PhD program.
Just turned 18 or 19, yeah. And so I still was shopping around for things to do. I was kind of
lost for the first couple of years really. But then I was very fortunate in several ways because
the math building at that time was physically attached to the physics building. So it was very
easy to wander over to the physics building from the math tower. And so I went to seminars and
colloquia and saw what was going on. And I got the impression, which was correct, that very exciting
things were going on in physics that used some of the mathematics that I really liked about symmetry
and some aspects of what's called analysis. And I met a very charismatic young professor named
David Gross who also happened to be the director of graduate studies. So he kind of greased the
wheels. Sure. I could make the transition and we hit it off right away. Was that a risk for him
to help you change? I mean, it's to sound like he had the power to make that happen.
A, he had the power to make it happen. I don't think it was a great risk for him. He was clearly
on the rise, kind of a star within the department. Although I think when I first met him, he still
didn't quite have tenure, but he got tenure just as at this point. And so it was him and then
Ken Wilson, who was developing his ideas, which are very famous within physics and got him another
prize a little later about what's called the renormalization group. So new mathematical
techniques for analyzing how you can calculate the behavior of particles within the reticle
frameworks, how they behave at short distances and how you can compare that with the
experiment. But the ideas were pretty vague. They didn't work in a specific theory, but very
clearly fun. And so I just decided that that was what I could try to do. So the stars were aligned.
They were very interesting things going on. I had a contact and a very promising relationship to
build on. And so I went into physics. I had taken a few physics courses. I had read the Feynman
lectures as they were coming out. They're now famous Feynman lectures. And I thought I
understood them, but in retrospect, clearly I did not understand most of what was in there.
So I did make the transfer into physics. I learned just enough to pass the exams
that were necessary. They waived some requirements about experiments. And
within a few months, David and I had done the work that later got the Nobel Prize.
Well, I want to ask before you even started that specific project, was your feeling at the time
with physics almost like, I guess, maybe 10 years ago when AI started to emerge,
it's obviously an extremely hot topic now. You could tell it was you were at a fundamental
leaping point for theoretical physics. I think it's more like what AI was like maybe 20 years ago.
Oh, yes. We have to go back. It's very unclear. Yeah. Well, and then was there any sense? I mean,
I think with AI, there's always been this great sense of danger. Was there any of that sense with
any of this work at all? No, no, no, no. That would be very remote. I think it was very
and that would that would be very remote because this to this was work on
well, very fundamental interactions. But basically what happens inside atomic nuclei
and what happens at accelerators and things, so things where you have to
go to great trouble to investigate. Sure. So the practical applications seem very remote and
right. And in fact, have not they have there aren't any. Yeah. To make a little story short.
OK. And that's the least if there are they're very futuristic. So this is like I remember in
the movie Oppenheimer, they talk about lighting the sky on fire. And then, yes, I know in CERN
open people were saying, oh, my goodness, this is going to create a black hole that will consume
the universe. Right. That stuff is a little overblown in terms of those concerns. Yes. Yeah. Yeah.
Well, that's right. Of course, the people who started nuclear physics had no idea that
it had the potential to make weapons. Right. It was a later development and later developments
did suggest that maybe playing around with very, very high energies could not ignite the atmosphere
in a fire, which was the issue with atomic bombs, but trigger a cosmic catastrophe where you change
the nature of the fundamental laws. Change the nature of space. That could be a problem.
It would be a big problem. But the good news is you'd never know what hit you. OK. Come out of
you at the speed of light. And yeah, but it's just over. It's just over. Yeah. You go over into a
purple haze. But those things, how should I say, they were very far from our minds and very far
from this was not an engineering endeavor. It was finding out what the laws are. And when you find
out what the laws are, they might have surprising implications. In this case, we found that
there was no, no hint of no real hint of possible catastrophes. Fantastic. Yeah.
That's great news. Yeah. So when you when you and David were working on
asymptotic freedom, was that something I should say? The thing that's relevant is that although
these conditions are difficult, the conditions of where you are probing the new laws that fund
them at very high energies, short distances, they're very hard to study under controlled
conditions. But in the history of the universe, they've occurred somewhere lots of time. Yeah.
With high energy cosmic rays all over the universe and in the big bang. And so, so just a priori
on that basis, the idea that you could trigger a catastrophe seemed very, very remote. Sure.
When you were when you and David were working on asymptotic freedom, did you kind of have the sense
that this was going to be as foundational as it was and lead to the Nobel Prize and other
career milestones you've had? Yeah, after the fact. I mean, sure. So it started out as
we as a very, from my point of view, a very theoretical investigation. I wanted to get a
thesis project. And this was putting together those ideas that I mentioned about the renormalization
group with that is study, which enabled you to study the behavior of theories at very high energies
and short distances in a precise mathematical way. With new kinds of theories, so called gauge
theories, which opened up possibilities for fundamental interactions that were previously
undreamed of. So the the best established theories of physics were and are in some sense still
the paradigms of what's called quantum electrodynamics, which is electricity and
magnetism merged with quantum theory and the general theory of relativity, which is both
of theories that have somewhat similar mathematical structures with high symmetry. And what happened
in the late 60s and very early 70s, just before we did this work was that people constructed a
generalization of electrodynamics and they sort of combined some ideas from electrodynamics and
general relativity into something called non-abelian gauge theories. And these were already
leading to a successful theory of what's called the weak interaction. So it wasn't clear how
successful it was going to be, but it appeared very promising at that time. And
there's something called the Landau ghost problem, which was a sort of disease of
electrodynamics and also in another way of general relativity. If you really
push the theory to very high energies or short distances, it would break down. The equations
would just become infinity equals infinity, nonsense, nonsense. And so
really inconsistency. You start the theory by assuming that there are concentrations of charges
at points in the, that's when electrons are concentrations of charges at points.
But then when you calculate the theory, you find that the charges
get canceled by effects of quantum fluctuations. So the theory kind of destroyed itself
conceptually. It worked, but only because you could sort of wall off this problem and not just,
if you refused to look, you swept it under the rug. But I wanted to see if you could do better in
these new kinds of theories, whether they would behave better. So that was the actual calculation
using these new techniques to describe new kinds of theories. And then the result was that the
theoretical problem did not appear in these theories. So that was a very, very profound
fact that made these theories seem really basic to our understanding of the world, potentially.
But I think that's the way that we can do it. And I think that's the way that we can do it.
That made these theories seem really basic to our understanding of the world potentially. And then
there were much more concrete issues with what's called the strong interaction, where there are
actual experiments that indicated that instead of the interaction getting more singular at short
distances, it kind of turned off at short distances when people took pictures of how things behave at
high energies. With a lot of image processing and theoretical insight, you can interpret these
experiments as saying that in fact, the interactions were getting weaker. So this was from a completely
different, much more empirical direction, an indication that you wanted a theory based on
these new classes of theories to describe the strong interaction. And David was very much coming
at it from that angle. He wanted to show to get a theory of the strong interaction. Well, actually,
what he wanted to do was show that it was not possible to get a theory of the strong interaction.
Oh, interesting.
Yes. So he was anticipating a negative result, but we got the positive result. And that
was a breakthrough. And so it was possible to think that after all, you could make a theory based on
standard principles of relativity and quantum mechanics and these new kinds of highly symmetrical
theories that would describe the strong interaction.
And that's what we worked out. Enough about the implications of these ideas to make them
theoretically coherent and make a very specific theory and make specific predictions about how
the strong interaction should behave, but also how it should be interpreted. And so
strong interaction should behave if it actually is described by this theory,
which at that time, the experimental evidence was very shaky, but we could say exactly what
you needed to do to reach a decision. And so there was kind of circumstantial evidence,
and the theory was pretty, and there was no real alternative that was similarly compelling.
So I thought there was a fair chance, and we wrote it down, that if you take the experiments in
this theoretical framework at face value, this is the theory of the strong interaction. There's no
alternative, which was incredible because the prospect, even a few months before, of having a
specific, precise theory of the strong interaction after decades of frustration and resignation,
I think, on the part of the community was just unmindboggling. And the
... So when you released these results, when you released this, a paper was the product of
a scientific paper that was a product of this? Yeah, a series of three papers.
That had to be, maybe, was it nerve-racking to release that because you know so many people
would be paying attention to it? A little bit. Actually, very few people understood it at first.
I mean, it was very... The analysis of the experiments that led to this interpretation
was kind of involved and subtle, and the calculations were very of a new kind,
and they were very subtle. But a few people, they'd get it right away.
The other thing was that the experimental evidence was not completely clear. We made clear
predictions about what should happen at much higher energies, but given the available data at the time,
and it wasn't compelling at all. You could imagine you had to have a sort of sense of humor and a lot
of optimism to interpret it in the way we wanted to interpret it. But we wrote at the time that
this is... If you take things at face value, this is the theory. And I, right away, thought and took
it that, well, if you've achieved the theory of one of the main forces of nature...
Yes, it's probably... Yeah.
... and sort of achieved what was at the top of the agenda of physics for decades, really, since
most of the 20th century, people wanted to understand what was holding atomic nuclei together,
and what were these things made... What was it made out of? And so I told David, I said to David
at the time, if it works out, if the experiments continue to point our way, that we'll get a Nobel
Prize for this. And David said, now it's not the kind of work that gets a Nobel Prize. No, I realized.
You knew.
Right?
You knew. Yeah.
Well, yeah, I knew. I mean, just it wasn't... I knew... Yeah, I mean, how often do you get to
explain and get the fundamental description of one of the basic forces of nature? Not very often.
That's every once every century or two?
Yes. Well, there are four interactions. It's happened four times. Well, actually,
in the case of gravity, it actually happened twice because there was Newton's theory and then
Einstein's theory, which is a more refined theory, quite different. But yeah, so it doesn't happen
every day.
So when that dawns on you, does that become a weight on you for your career, that you're carrying
this big theory with you?
Well, certainly a platform, but also there's a lot of responsibility with that, right?
I didn't think of it that way. But it was a huge opportunity.
Yeah.
I didn't... So this breakthrough opened up many new directions. Because you could
understand how things behaved at very high energies and very extreme conditions, suddenly
you could, with confidence, make, or at least credibility, make models of the earliest moments
of the Big Bang. Before this breakthrough, it appeared that when things got very, very
close together in the Big Bang, very dense in the Big Bang, the strong interaction becomes
totally intractable. It was just a black... No one knew what to do. But when you learn that
the interactions kind of turn off and become weak, suddenly you can do it. And so that
opened up the very early universe and that led to important developments. It also meant
that you could analyze what was going to happen at high energy accelerators in much more
insightful and quantitative ways. So for instance, if you... Well, this only became clear years
later, but eventually people wanted to discover something, wanted to observe something called
the Higgs particle. But to figure out how you're going to produce this Higgs particle
and how are you going to... It's very unstable, so how are you going to detect that it ever
was produced? You needed a lot of control about how things behaved at high energies and how you
can relate the theory to experiments. So working out that kind of thing was a big deal.
And then the other thing is that, okay, so now we had a theory of the strong interaction,
weak interaction, electromagnetic and gravity, and they had kind of a similar mathematical
structure. Could they be unified into a bigger structure? So that was another thing. So all
these things, suddenly many new directions were opened up and that kept me busy for quite a while.
Yeah. I guess that's what I was thinking about when I said the weight of it was... I mean,
this creates a career for you, it creates a career for a lot of people, a lot of work to be done
that's still being done. And I guess I was wondering if it fell on you to organize that
or if the community just sort of self-governs and does that by themselves.
Well, I didn't think of it as a weight. I thought of it more as rocket fuel.
Yeah, sure, sure, sure. Yeah. Well, my glass was half empty there. No, that's great.
But yeah, I did feel some responsibility to live up to these opportunities, but mostly I just
thought of them as opportunities. The weight was, well, would it really be true?
Sure. Yeah. Well, you're pretty confident you have to validate, right?
I wasn't confident, actually. Oh, okay.
The data was... I mean, we
interpreted the data in a very bold way. The data was really kind of tentative, I would say.
Well, suggestive, but not definitive. And the really definitive data was almost 20 years later.
Yeah. So that was a weight. And then there was the weight of,
okay, when are we going to get a Nobel Prize? Right. So that ended up happening,
was it about 30 years later? Yes.
But it had been on your mind the entire time. I guess, from my perspective...
Well, yes. I mean, as I said, I thought eventually it would happen right away.
But I thought as soon as it became clear that the theory was correct, then it would be very quick
to get the prize. But that was unrealistic now, in retrospect, for two reasons. One is that
the downside of having a very precise theory is that the tests have to be made.
Yeah. Because the
Nobel Prize committees are very conservative. They don't want to give the prize for something
that's later proved to be incorrect. Sure.
So weight on the tests, that was one thing. And then the other thing was our work was based on
both experimental and theoretical work by others that was founded by the Nobel Prize committee.
And we were sort of... There was a kind of queue. So they had to get theirs first, logically.
That makes sense. Yeah. I just thought... I guess,
and then by 2004, I'm trying to think. For something that happened 30 years prior,
does that almost feel like that was a lifetime ago when the award comes? I mean, sort of...
Well, sort of. Yeah. It was a long time ago. It was quite a while ago, and a lot had happened
since then. Yeah. It makes me think of Paul
McCartney talks about his life as a beetle. And he says that just seems like someone else's
life almost, because that's a much bigger time gap for him.
Yeah. Well, it's also a much different experience. Yeah. Very different. Yeah.
Different rocket fuel. So although the Nobel Prize came later,
within the physics community, and I've gotten tenure at a great place and was
where I've gotten a lot of recognition within the community now. And myself, I felt I had,
maybe not perfectly, but I had really advanced. I had exploited a lot of the opportunities
that were there, and I really done my bit. So it wasn't... And because the work kind of...
A lot of the work I did later grew out, grew naturally out of that development. I still
felt connected to it. And more than that, a vast community effort had gone into making,
exploiting these things, especially for analyzing what's going to happen at accelerators.
And so a lot of work in both theory and experiment. The calculations could be done
much more accurately than we did and carried much further. The whole way of doing experimental
high energy physics changed because suddenly quarks and gluons were real things. And you could
sort of see them in what are called jets. So the focus turned towards analyzing properties of
jets. It was just a different world. So people knew what they were doing, in other words.
Sure, sure.
And had to readjust a lot of the technology to exploit this way of doing things. So from being
a kind of guerrilla warfare with a small band of people outside the mainstream,
which was what we were initially, it became absolutely armies of people pushing this forward.
And so living through that whole process, there was a connection, even though the time was...
There was a lot of time. It's not as if it was a dream that passed and then you wake up
and it's a different world. Not like Rip Van Winkle where you're sitting.
Sure, sure. Yeah. Makes sense. So you get the call in 2004. What's that process like? What happens
when you go into Stockholm?
Well, okay. So starting with the call, as I said, from very early on, I thought it was likely that
we'd get a prize for this eventually, but there was a queue and I thought we might jump the queue,
but it didn't happen. But the people in front of us in the line, so to speak, had been served by
2000. So at that point I thought, okay, any year now it's going to happen. And so I knew when the
announcements would be each year, and it's a very specific time when they make the public announcement.
Actually, the way they phrase it is not before, but usually that means at the time. So unless
there's some kind of dispute or a last minute change of heart, they... No sooner means that's
when they announce it. Okay. So we knew that it would be announced at 12 noon Stockholm time,
which is 6 a.m. on the East Coast, which is where it was, in Cambridge, in fact.
And so I had a very difficult time sleeping because I knew I'm anticipating this possibility.
And on that night, which was, I guess, I don't know, we're talking about October 4th, 2004,
I wasn't able to sleep. And so about five o'clock after a restless night, I looked up at our
little bedside clock with the red LED lights and it said five o'clock. Okay. So I said,
all right, well, if the call comes at six, you're not sleeping, Frank. You might as well get up,
take a shower, and you'll be ready. Okay. So I got into the shower. And just as I was
beginning the shower, five minutes into it, Betsy came by, knocked on the door, and came in with our
mobile phone and said, I hadn't heard the phone call. She came in with the phone and said,
Frank, there's a call for you. Someone said, with an accent, says they're calling from Sweden
and they want to talk to you. I think you should take this call. And so I got out of the shower
and I took the call right away. I didn't draw you off or anything. It was something wet. And
yet that was it. It was not. So what I didn't know was that when they know what's going to happen,
they called earlier. And so that was it. And the other thing I didn't know was that
my anticipation was that the phone call would be, congratulations, you won the Nobel Prize.
Goodbye. But it wasn't that way at all. There were several people from Sweden, friends who wanted to
congratulate and other people who wanted to give instructions for how to deal with the press and so
and what you should not do and all of the details it was going to happen. So I was just
I was there soaking wet, dripping wet and listening to this for about 20 minutes.
So that was the initial experience. I thought I wouldn't go to process any of the instructions
that were being given to me on that call. But then I wanted to call my parents right away
because they're very important to them, I think. And I did right away. So I'll add to that.
That was probably five thirty. And my father answered the phone and he was really furious.
He said, what do you know what time it is? Whatever you're selling, I don't want any.
And if you call again, I'm going to report you. I said, no, no, no, it's your son.
And so that was a very special moment also. And then, OK, so then I was like,
then OK, so then I dried off and got dressed and six o'clock the announcement was made.
And right away there were phones was ringing off the hook and eventually we just took it off.
And and there was an AP stringer who knocked on our door and it was so it was it was a lot of fun.
Yeah, it was very and then there's a whirlwind of things. And then the press press conference and so
and you have to get clothes. Yeah. And it's a great party. So you get to talk and yeah.
Yeah. So it's a weak law. And another thing I didn't realize is that is what the nature of
the actual process is where you get the point is not just a kind of evening event.
It's a complete a whole week of one extraordinary event after another. You have dinner with the king.
You have the great dinner in the city hall with thousands of people and very elaborate service.
Singing and dancing. What was your favorite part?
I think my favorite part was after the dinner. This is the dinner of the king or no, the dinner
in city hall. See, OK, there's this there's music and dancing wait until the night. I like that.
I like that. It's a beautiful place and lots of happy people. Yeah. And everybody's I should have
said another aspect of it is everyone's dressed up and kind of 19th century academic costume
with a white tie, not black tie, white tie. And the women are in gorgeous gowns. And so.
So yeah, that sounds like out of a dream. It is. It's like a fairy tale.
Very much like. And so you get, you know, a medal and I think a custom painted
diploma. Diploma. Right. Yeah. And each one is different. Yeah.
I have a very silly question for you about that. So you receive this stuff at these ceremonies.
Do you just put that in your luggage and fly with it home or is it somehow like
specially couriered back to your home? Like that's obviously like a very historic.
Those are very historic things that you're receiving. Like how does that work?
It's a lot of good. Yeah, I just put it like that.
I was I was I was wondering that because we did the the Templeton Prize ceremony in 22.
And I remember you I think you flew to Sweden right after it. And I remember it was like you
get this beautiful diploma from them as well. And then I remember we left and it was just like
cardboard and masking tape around it to carry it back. And I thought how else would I was I
don't know if I was expecting it to be true. I brought it. I brought it back on Amtrak.
You brought it back. I brought it back on the Amtrak train and I put it in my car.
All right. Yeah. We framed it. Yeah.
Yeah. Sure. I was like I was like why do they trust me? I didn't know if it was like the Stanley
Cup where they have the guys in white gloves like bringing around an armory cars or what.
OK. Thank you for answering my very very silly question. But I had as a middle
aged suburban dad I had to know. So I wanted to ask you also later in your career you've had
I think two names stand out to me. Axions and time crystals. Two of the cooler names.
Well also any and any on how do you how do you name things.
Well each one is a different story. So.
Axions were. It's probably the most interesting story. When I was still in college.
I was home for the summer and went on a grocery shopping expedition with my mother and saw on
on the shelf a detergent laundry detergent named Axion. And I said to myself wow that
wow that really sounds like a particle. I was like you know there's protons and muons and pions
and this Axion. It's a nice weak root. And I said to myself if I ever get a chance to name a particle
call it Axion. And a few years later it was just a few years. Yeah. There's like four or five years
later there was a problem with an axial current and a new kind of particle that arises in
in that connection. I mean that's not the most important aspect of it but part of it was enough
to do. There's enough of an excuse to actually call it Axion. That's cool. Yeah. So I did that.
And that would mean the crucial part was getting it past the editors of physical review letters
where we published it because if they had known that I was naming it after a laundry detergent
that would never be wild. Yeah. They're very conservative about these things. Yeah. So I was
very fortunate that I could drag in the axial current and say oh that's what that's what I was
named after. Named after the axial current. Yeah. So that was that one. Then
anyons was in a way the most straightforward. For many years people physicists had thought that
all particles could be divided into two kingdoms. Fermions and bosons they're called which have
quite different properties. Let me let me backtrack one second. One of the great achievements of
quantum theory is to show that very different concepts of what a particle is. So there's a wave
there's a wave aspect and a particle aspect that actually in quantum mechanics there's a more
general description that has both aspects. So it's neither a wave nor a particle but we sometimes
people call it a wave, waveical or that that is unites all entities all physical entities can be
described in this very general way. So things as different as electrons and photons which seem to
be so different in their properties can both be described using waveicals as people's.
But so that's a great unification but when you come to describe not single particles but
more than one like two or more then they're very different and there are two classes there are
bosons which basically like to do the same thing and there are fermions that dislike doing the same
thing. The dislike is the the liking to do the same thing is maybe most dramatically illustrated
in a laser where you see you have lots of photons that all want to be in the same color moving in
the same direction and the disliking doing the same thing for a fermion which electrons are an
example is what makes the periodic table work atoms build up with different states different
energy levels for the different electrons and many other phenomena. And for many years people
thought though those were the only two possibilities and I was not happy with the proofs that I had
read but it was in the back of my mind that there was there was not a holes in the argument and
by a kind of circuitous path I was led to
think that if you had particles not in three dimensions but in two dimensions
they wouldn't necessarily be particle either fermions or bosons that there are more general
possibilities and that's and then closer analysis shows that that that's the case.
So in the mathematical formulation when you have bosons there's a positive and a negative
bosons there's a plus sign in the wave function when there's fermions that's a minus sign
when you have any but when but there are other possibilities that involve complex numbers
that kind of interpolate between one and minus one technically it's phases or complex numbers
with magnitude unity any any of them. So since you can have any of these things in a continuous
range I call them anyons and that was accepted and they become a very very big topic since then.
At first I mean in the early days was kind of playful but it's become very
very serious as a possible technology for quantum information processing and quantum computers
and just describing what happens in two dimensions. So that's anyons time crystals actually is
is something that my wife Betsy who you know is largely responsible for.
I was
thinking about how you might have states of matter or physical systems that behave
that naturally organize themselves into periodic structures in time. So crystals are
periodic structures in space but this would be things that spontaneously form periodic structures
in time. And this was actually when we were walking when I was walking across England was
when I was thinking about this and Betsy was driving us a meeting into sort of the camp manager
and so but we had lots of time as we talked about it and she asked me to explain it and I
told her it's reaching for analogies and I said it's like a crystal but in time instead of space.
And she said it's like a crystal but in time instead of space. And I said I'm sorry I'm sorry
and I said it's like a crystal but in time instead of space. And she asked me what I was
what I called it and I said well I call it spontaneous breaking of time translation symmetry.
Very remarkable. No no no no no no no no you you it's a time crystal and that
and she really insisted on it. I had misgivings about it I thought it was kind of too showy or too.
Well it made it into Avengers Endgame so. Yeah it made a but it was a great it turned out to be a
great thing to call it time because it really caught the imagination of the public but also
of scientists. A great name is really really important. Yeah I've learned. Does that does
that help you even with like does it move you up in experimental cues or anything
to have something that becomes that popular. Absolutely yeah yeah absolutely people it's it's
having a name for something
can really focus attention on so people experimenters can say what they're doing.
I'm making a time crystal. Yeah. Or I'm looking for any odds I'm looking for axions.
Whereas if you didn't have the name you'd have to go through a long long and dance about what it is.
And different people doing similar things wouldn't have a common language and yeah so
names are really really important. Yeah. And also
how should I say when you've named something you've real you've
taken your concept you have to refine the concept. Tell us you know define it. What what are you
talking about. And that is a very important discipline to be able to say damn it this is
what I'm talking about. This this word encapsulates this captures some years of thought. Yeah yeah.
And and actually in all those cases when I named the thing I realized a lot but
it's grown into something later it grew each of these things has grown into something much larger
in many directions that I didn't anticipate. Yeah. But well did you firstly to have the name
because you know I got the paper still get keep getting quoted and it sort of attaches to me as
the founding father of this even though it's stuff now that is very very very very very very
even though it's stuff now that is very very
remotely related tenuously related to the initial conceptions. Yeah I mean like when
with any with any on did you envision quantum computing. Absolutely not no absolutely not no
it's just it but it's sort of like in the in the case of asymptotic freedom and quantum
chromodynamics I realized that it was a very very fundamental expansion of our understanding of the
physical world. So it would lead it could lead in really important directions was really foundational
you know so it wasn't just adding a brick here it was adding that it was changing the foundations
and so I although I didn't anticipate all these developments I'm not shocked that there have been
major developments coming out. Sure. That makes sense. I have I have two more questions for you
one is pretty quick and the other one I will let you dictate how much time you'd like to spend on
it. I want to say it's a really fun tradition for me it's been the last 10 years we go to an NBA
game every year. Yes. First one was in Miami and we saw LeBron and Chris Bosch Dwayne Wade.
This year we typically I know you're a big LeBron fan and we typically try to go see him
but this year at the scheduling workouts we saw Minnesota come. Yes. Who are you watching and
liking in the playoffs this year when we're in the conference final season. Yeah. Who are who's your
favorite. Well I think I'd better say Boston. That's that's Boston. Boston's an interesting
I like Boston because they kind of distributed there. They're a real team. I mean they have
stars but they're not dominated by a single star. Yeah. Tate and Brown and White and so and
even Al Horford plays you know all these guys play play roles and they're all important so that
that's nice. Of course I was rooting for the L.A. Lakers but they didn't come through and I also but
I like Denver. Yeah. Also for two reasons because I really think Yokech is so cool and so singular
his kind of approach to the game and just the effortlessness where he tosses in these
floaters. Yeah. He seems to be playing a different game and he's like a man among boys sometimes.
Yeah. He's so fundamentally skilled. Yes. It's really impressive to watch him. Yeah. And and
and you know that I've really been impressed by how after losing two games at home and looking
really bad they came back. So now it's it's not clear how it's going to end but they showed a lot
of character I think. Yeah. In coming back that way. So I and so also you know since they are the
team that beat the Lakers I'm kind of saying well you know if if they wouldn't go on to win the
championship that means that the Lakers lost to the champs. Yeah. They could be the second best.
They could be the second best. Yeah. I've always I've always felt that when my team loses in the
playoffs too. I'll say that I really enjoy it. We sat in the section that was kind of behind the
Minnesota bench. We went to that game this year and the joy that they had and like that team was
just a lot of fun. They're a team. And I they that's a team I never really thought about but
now I actually really like a lot just because of that experience. Yeah. So there are a lot of
teams to like in the in the you know all the you know all the teams really that are that are still
in the playoffs plus the plus other ones that they all have. I mean it's the whole well there
are some there are some teams that are very sour obviously you know these are things where
they had great expectations that weren't fulfilled and stars that kind of didn't come through or
injured or whatever. And that leaves a bad taste. But among but mostly it's a wonderful kind of
human enterprise to see people cooperating to try to do something remarkable. Yeah. They put an
enormous effort. They're incredibly skilled and gifted and you know like another species in many
ways. And and they're how should I say they've they've devoted themselves to to something bigger
than themselves. So you might say it's it's it's just a game and not serious and so but but you
know it's it's you could say similar things about astronomy or art or things that people think of as
as the ultimate human expression. People get very very good at something and put on a great show.
And it's wonderful to see. It's a good healthy way to take people who are naturally hyper
competitive and put that to use. Yeah. Yeah. That's a question. Is the world of theoretical
physics ever competitive. It's always always competitive. Yeah. You're always I mean to me
it sounds like always on top of what's going on always pushing things further faster and trying
to beat anyone else to the punch. Yeah. Yeah. And there's also a sort of defending territory. Sure.
Sure. But it's all how should I say it's it's much more sublimated than in sports where there's a
score and it's and and mostly it's cooperative. But you know ultimately like the Nobel Prize it's
it's for any particular any particular year it's given to most three people for typically one
development. Yeah. And so but that's not the way science works. Typically it's not
how should I say the prizes are digital but sure the process is analog. Many people make
kind of contributions at different levels and so but yeah so there's but only one guy gets the job
and one guy gets the prize. Right. So so inevitably that makes for competitive situations.
And also there's a lot of the rewards in this kind of work are ego rewards.
It's people can live well on professor salaries and so
and but they don't. But some of the people in this world are really really super brilliant
and could make a lot more money elsewhere. Sure. The big rewards though are freedom you get
it and an ego reward you feel you're doing something permanent value and beautiful.
It really is kind of like an art in many ways. So that's but if you're going to have ego rewards
then egos get wrapped up in it. Yeah. I wasn't I never I hadn't thought about that. If you ever
had like a star student that you were disappointed to see get lured away to finance or something that
maybe you thought could have followed the the academia out and done very well.
Yeah well yes I but yes I have had students who've done that including a couple of the very best ones
yeah the most promising. But I think I it's like having a child that
ultimately you know you can you can teach and it's hopefully inspire and show them but ultimately
it's their life and they choose and I think if they're happy and
and doing and not doing crime something destructive that's fine. I mean science
you know science is a big community and any individual I think is replaceable in some sense.
Okay some people might things might happen faster due to to some individual make an
outstanding contribution but even even giants like Newton and Einstein if you really analyze it
everything they discovered would have been discovered anyway. Sure. Maybe 10 years later.
Right. Well in Einstein's case maybe 10 years later at most in Newton's case
probably longer because it was a smaller community and must it was much less efficient but nowadays
with a gigantic community and very rapid communication and so forth I think
the contribution of any individual is not essential. You know things will have so
so if my student if I have a student is very promising wants to do something else
God bless him or her. Right. If that their passion leads elsewhere
insecurity elsewhere. I don't feel let down. Yeah. Okay. I think okay last question this time I promise.
One of one of my perspectives I think about as I'm doing this project is
someone 50 years from now digging up this project and listening to it.
Where where do you think the conqueror and the rest of the world will be in 50 years.
Well I'm writing a book now called futures and sort of thinking about this and it could go in
very different directions and there are possible catastrophes I think climate change could be
catastrophic certainly nuclear war could be catastrophic but I'm very optimistic actually.
Good. I want to hear that. If
you think about what the world was like say 100 years ago
most people lived on farms and they were famines that many people and computers were just not even
on the horizon and look at speculations about what life would be like at that time. It's kind
of pathetic. Right. What actually happened even though in that 100 years we've had two world wars
many smaller
plagues
and the reason that things have improved despite all that is that we understand the world a lot
better and technology keeps getting better and better and during the 20th century and continuing
to the 21st century I think we've understood what matter is and what we're going to see in the
future what life is and now even what mind is at levels that were just not there previously
and that gives us enormous power
and having that power most people want to do good by other people not all but enough
yeah and producing you know producing more wealth
more opportunities for expanding mind for living longer living healthier
the kind of tools we have now for mind expansion I think all that is very exciting very promising
and so that's I'm optimistic there may be bumps in the road there may be very big bumps in the road
and there could be catastrophes but I'd like to think not and if not then I think
the future of humanity and even more of mind in the universe is just awesome yeah
well you've been right about a lot of stuff over the years so I'm taking it I'm taking this one as
truth for the next 50 I appreciate that well thank you for spending so much time with me I
this has been great for me I hope you've enjoyed it yeah and we'll be seeing you soon okay