This is Concord Storytellers and I have with me a very special guest.
Concord resident, neighbor, friend, turns out amazing squash player, mediocre golfer
and a 2023 Massachusetts Lawyers Weekly Lawyer of the Year.
I actually Googled you for the first time ever this week since, you know, thank you
so much for coming on and doing an episode with me.
Charlotte Whitmore and you have, I think, one of the coolest jobs that I have ever heard.
You're one of the first people I met when I moved here and you told me what you did
and I just, my jaw dropped.
I said I'm basically living among a superhero.
So can you describe for me what you do with the Innocence Project?
Yeah, absolutely.
So right now I have two roles.
I am a senior staff attorney at the Boston College Innocence Program and the Boston College
Innocence Program is a clinical legal education program out of BC Law where we investigate
and litigate wrongful conviction cases along with second and third year law students.
So through my work at, I'll call it BCIP for short, through my work at BCIP, everything
I do for a case from case intake to gathering documents to reviewing documents, interviewing
witnesses and of course all the litigation that goes into writing a wrongful conviction
I do alongside of law students.
So we're teaching them how to litigate these cases by actually doing it.
And recently I also started about a little over a year ago as the legal director of a
relatively new nonprofit called Life After Justice.
Life After Justice is unique because it seeks to eradicate wrongful convictions but it's
founded and led by people who themselves have been exonerated after wrongful convictions.
So we have a unique perspective there being led by people who have been directly impacted
by the criminal justice system.
How does that dovetail with the Innocence Project?
So the term the Innocence Project is actually trademarked and it belongs to the Innocence
Project in New York which was founded by Barry Schack and Peter Neufeld in 1992.
That was the first Innocence Project.
The Innocence Project was founded right after DNA became started to be used in criminal
cases and Barry and Peter saw this way for them to investigate potential wrongful convictions
by testing evidence for DNA that had not been previously tested.
So the Innocence Project still primarily works on cases only cases where DNA can conclusively
prove innocence and they're a national organization.
So they work on cases all over the country.
Since they founded the Innocence Project many many statewide Innocence Programs or Innocence
Projects have been founded.
I think there are high 60s low 70s of Innocence Programs nationwide and those programs together
form the Innocence Network.
And we meet annually and we share ideas and thoughts via email and help each other out
with cases that we're litigating but we are all separate nonprofits.
Some are associated with law schools.
Some are standalone 501c3s.
Everyone has their own criteria.
Most are state specific and many now investigate cases that do not involve DNA evidence.
Most of my cases do not involve DNA evidence.
Gotcha.
Yeah I watched as prep for this I watched this show The Innocence Files on Netflix.
It's a great show I recommend to anybody to watch.
It's a nine part limited docu-series and they talked a bit about that and they mentioned
that this term forensic science was actually a very bad name for what this was before DNA
evidence was launched and it was really investigators detectives coming up with creative methods
of solving crimes but there was no actual science no rigor of science behind it so that
I think the first three episodes were about bite mark cases and how this science that
became famous because someone presented bite marks in a Ted Bundy's case became the rage
for detectives and ended up being kind of very very bad science and resulted in a number
of wrongful convictions.
Have you I guess have you said you haven't dealt you don't deal much with DNA evidence
and some of these I guess bad forensic evidence cases like what sort of stuff happens in the
cases that you work on.
Well I do.
So a number of my cases have involved DNA evidence to some extent.
It's just that they're not cases where DNA alone could conclusively prove innocence so
we retest evidence and then we simultaneously reinvestigate the case by talking to witnesses
experts things like that but but as you noted there's a there's a number of sciences that
have significantly changed over the past few decades.
For example I've had I've had three or four cases recently that are that were arson convictions
but the field of fire science has significantly changed since the 80s and 90s and for example
a lot of the burn patterns that investigators thought were indicative of accelerant which
would indicate that a fire was an arson as opposed to an accident.
We now know are equally present in accidental fires as if fires caused by accelerant and
these types of patterns don't necessarily mean that accelerant was involved.
Other types of sciences that have changed are shaken baby science or abusive head trauma.
There's been significant changes in our understanding of symptoms that may or may not be caused
by by abuse as well as hair microscopy.
So in the 80s and 90s technicians would look at a hair under a microscope and as well as
perhaps a hair that was found on a victim's body for instance and they would testify to
a you know degree of scientific certainty and sometimes as a conclusive match that the
hair found on the victim's body matched as in you know 100 percent to the exclusion of
all others a hair from the suspect and that that science has been largely debunked where
a technician could testify that a hair was similar or a hair did not match but cannot
make a conclusive match and so we've been as an innocence community reviewing many many
cases in which the hair microscopy testimony was it was extremely misleading if not false.
Gotcha and I mean I have to imagine that there are new topics that come in every year is
that is that a big part of this annual network meeting you have is to say here's some new
problems we're finding with with evidence gathering such as the hair microscopy is that
something that you say okay well we're going to go back to all these cases that we have
on file and look for ones that match this new scientific method and we'll look for one
that we think we could possibly win.
Absolutely yeah so we'll hear from litigators across the country who are experienced in
these types of cases we'll have experts you know arson experts or DNA experts or eyewitness
identification experts come in and speak at our conferences and we we definitely try to
learn from each other both in litigation strategies learning about the science but also the best
ways to go about reinvestigating these types of cases for example the hair microscopy that
we were just talking about there's been a lot of collaboration in reviewing those cases
with the prosecution in many states because it's agreed upon that that testimony was not
accurate and so we also share strategies on how best to collaborate with government agencies.
Gotcha.
I want to go back in time a bit and just talk about your pathway to this career did you
always want to be a lawyer growing up?
No I wanted to be a teacher.
Okay and you are now.
That's true different than I than I imagined I all through undergrad I planned on being
a teacher my brother did teach for America I wanted to teach in an inner city and then
when I was a senior in college I randomly came across a job listing for a paralegal
at the federal defenders in New York which is the federal public defender system and
I applied for the job drove down to New York got it and that and that job changed my whole
trajectory as a you know 22 year old straight out of college I was spending three or four
days a week in very high security federal detention centers in Manhattan and Brooklyn
meeting with clients helping attorneys investigate and defend these clients and that is certainly
what made me want to go to law school and be a public defender or work in the innocence
field.
Awesome and I saw there was a Dartmouth magazine article about you it was your first case Eugene
Gillyard when you graduated law school?
That was my one of my first cases at the Pennsylvania Innocence Project so after I graduated from
law school I did two different clerkships for judges in Pennsylvania and then went to
work for the Pennsylvania Innocence Project and Eugene was my first successful case out
of Pennsylvania.
Wow and this is where this is where again my jaw dropped when I saw this description
of you knocking on doors in North Philadelphia trying to find the truth and eventually it
says here that Eugene Gillyard believed that a man who went by the name of Rolex was the
actual offender the one of the murderers of this shop clerk and it says that you went
to talk to Rolex and within minutes he had confessed to the crime.
How does that work?
Well every case is different every investigation is different.
When I investigate cases I think one of the strengths that we have is that I'm not looking
for a particular answer and I come off hopefully as relatively non-threatening and non-coercive
and just asking the witness you know if they remember the crime if they're willing to talk
and saying that I want to know the truth.
If the person whose case I'm investigating is involved I want to know that I want to
know that sooner rather than later and if he or she is not then of course I want to
know that information and so I'm really just trying to get the witness to open up and tell
me whatever he or she remembers.
Many many people are not willing to talk a lot of these cases bring up some significant
trauma for witnesses and victims and family members of the of the wrongfully convicted.
In that particular case I was fortunate in the fact that by the time I was face to face
with Rolex who was incarcerated at that time Eugene had already been in jail for this crime
for well over a decade and Rolex was ready to come clean his conscience had had caught
up with him and he wanted to do the right thing and so I was able to just give him the
platform that he was looking for to tell the truth.
It was like something that yeah I guess after that much time has passed this thing happened
almost a lifetime ago for somebody and like you said just the right person has to come
along with with the right conduit to make something right because I mean he I mean I
guess I just from my like five hours of watching that documentary I mean people can say all
kinds of things especially it seems like people who are in in law enforcement and prosecution
have such a caseload going on that you say you're looking for the truth it's almost
like they're trying to just process cases and get them done and check off some boxes
and it maybe seems like they take sort of a different tactic when they're talking to
some of these people and trying to not just like find the truth but almost just like get
work done.
Is that something that you run across where I don't know if I explained that correctly.
No I think yeah there's been a lot of research done recently about different types of biases
that are present within many different stakeholders in the criminal justice system police prosecutors
defense attorneys witnesses victims and so one of the main factors that we are looking
at in the innocence community is confirmation bias that comes into play in a police investigation
and it's not in it's typically not intentional it's a very human way to process information
if you develop a theory or infer you know the first evidence that comes in points in
a certain direction you're going to naturally interpret additional evidence under that umbrella
so evidence that fits that theory becomes more important to you and evidence that doesn't
fit that theory you might subconsciously ignore and we see that a lot in police investigations
and in fact many police departments are now starting to train for confirmation bias to
teach officers that how this comes into play that it exists to be aware of it to try to
guard against that.
That's great and I saw that even they were talking about even with eyewitnesses that
one in four people looking through a photo book at a potential someone who committed
the crime that one in four people get the person wrong on photo identification and there
was all kinds of interesting science around that like if someone attacks you your brain
will naturally focus more on the weapon the knife or the gun or the fist or whatever and
that the face is just something that we as humans don't really process correctly especially
in a time of high stress and that when you're sitting down like all you want to do is make
sure that the person who's responsible for this is held accountable and so that's what
leads to all these I guess like bad witness identification cases.
Is that something you run across as well in some of the work you've done a lot?
Yes absolutely I have personally put on experts in eyewitness identification to testify to
pretty much exactly what you just explained and many other factors that we now know affect
the reliability of an ID.
Juries used to be presented largely with this person this eyewitness is either correct or
lying right now we know what the most likely answer is neither of those.
But there are many many genuine honest mistakes made by eyewitnesses due to a number of factors
you know you mentioned stress weapons focus our memory for faces in particular is not
as good as we thought there's also you know the time between witnessing the incident and
the first ID procedure multiple ID procedures can affect memory.
All of these things there experts have studied this intensely over the last few decades and
that has significantly changed both pretrial ID processes as well as post-conviction hearings
where we are looking at the reliability of an idea that was given a number of years ago.
Gotcha.
One thing I was wondering about is with these new scientific concepts coming out there are
really two parts to this question one you seem to be and I think the Innocence Network seems
to be at the cutting edge of forensic science or whatever science might be involved in in
criminal law does that take a long time to propagate around the US to smaller communities
and things like that like if I went back to my hometown small town in Tennessee if I talk
to a lawyer there are they going to know about eyewitness problems and you know bite mark
issues things like that or is that does that take a long time to get out there?
Yeah I think it takes some time and some of these issues we've known about some of these
changes in science we've known about for longer than others and I do think that attorneys
with the Innocence Network when they get a case that presents this specific issue they
become an expert in that issue when you have an arson case when you have an eyewitness
case by learning from the experts right so we work very closely with researchers with
the fire investigators the experts who can teach us the science and then we do try to
pass that on as much as possible to the to the defense part in general through trainings
you know I think innocence attorneys in their home states are doing trainings to defense
attorneys all the time on these issues so I don't know the short answer to your question
is I don't know because but I think that there are significant strides being made in those
areas.
Cool and do you think that the bar for conviction is getting higher?
That is a really good question.
I would like to think so I think that the I think that people are still getting convicted
of very serious felonies on significantly less evidence than many people would think
would be necessary but I also think our criminal justice system is doing a you know every year
that goes by we're doing a better job of making sure that evidence put forth to a jury is
reliable both scientifically and in other fashions so I guess the best way I can answer
that is I think we're doing better than we were you know 10-20 years ago but there's
still significant room for improvement.
I guess along those lines too one thing that I was struck by when reading about some of
these cases is that you or someone else in your network will find compelling evidence
of someone's innocence whether it's a confession from somebody else there's DNA evidence that
says this person is eliminated as a suspect and might even say that this other person
is matched to it years can go by or a case will not be reopened because the original
prosecutors are unwilling to reopen it.
How does that happen?
Why does that happen?
I don't understand it.
Yeah there are a lot of reasons why it happens.
I mean one thing is that our criminal justice system that's often not always but often values
finality over justice so we have in every state is different but we have laws set up
to protect finality to make it particularly difficult to reopen cases.
In Massachusetts we're fortunate we have a very we have we have a post-conviction statute
that is intent on finding justice so in Massachusetts we can bring a new trial motion a motion
asking a judge to vacate a conviction at any time upon a showing that justice may not have
been done.
That's a statute that is aimed at finding the truth.
That being said there still can be procedural bars to reopening a case right if something
has already been litigated or if you don't have newly discovered evidence then you can
face procedural bars to getting back into court in Massachusetts and in other states.
I think the prosecutors again I think it comes back to often comes back to confirmation bias
that we talked about before right they still believe you know most prosecutors are good
people who want the right outcome but sometimes they are blinded by the fact that this person
was already convicted by a jury of his or her peers and it's really hard to see beyond
that at times.
That being said there is there's a movement in the innocence world led by prosecutors
to create conviction integrity units in their own offices where they themselves are reviewing
potential wrongful convictions to determine if they think that an injustice has been done.
So while we do face sometimes in our case work what I would view as unjust opposition
by prosecutors we also have had many cases where we work alongside the prosecutor to
try to come to the right result.
That's great I mean I think along the lines of confirmation bias imagine just even just
psychologically going into the office every day and having a team there that's dedicated
to the fact that we might get some stuff wrong relieves some pressure and also just lets
you think every day subconsciously there might have gotten one of these wrong so let's just
have that as part of the system.
I imagine that helps things out a lot.
It's good to hear that those are that those are happening.
So I wanted to mention too I remember I think it was two summers ago that we were golfing
and I think we were playing nine just a quick nine the sixth or seventh hole and you just
you got a phone call so I'm sorry I have to take this and then you got off and said yeah
one of my clients is getting released from prison today and you were like I'm so sorry
I have to go we're like yeah you can go we'll drive you if we if you need to.
Can you talk a little bit about that and just what it's like to go in and see one of your
clients be set free.
Yeah I mean that is bar none the best part of this job.
It's the day that you get to be with your client is as they walk out of prison that
particular client had served 35 years for a fire that he did not set.
It's hard to put into words what that feeling is like because it's incredibly tragic.
It's incredibly sad but also it's this it's this moment of pure joy when your client walks
out of prison into the sunlight into freedom for the first time in that many years and
what you and he or she have been working for together usually for most of our cases from
the from the day I get a letter from a potential client to the day that he or she walks out
of prison I think is averaging somewhere between five and seven years.
So we've been working together for a long time and working towards that day.
But there's always an undercurrent of tragedy as well.
Yeah of course.
I mean this is you're someone who's been living for decades with an identity.
I mean if you're if you're convicted of a serious felony and you're living with that
identity in a in a in a in a in a it's just false it's just wrong.
I can't imagine every day being saying that I have done this thing and you know you didn't
do it.
I even saw some of these cases where some of the wrongfully incarcerated were saying
I started to doubt myself.
Did I did I sleepwalk did I did something happen.
They almost start to believe these things that are being said about them.
But I mean I have to imagine that's a huge burden lifted when they walk out.
I did see that in a lot of these cases there's some financial compensation for the people
and it ranged.
I saw everything from someone got fifty thousand dollars a year for 10 years and ran out.
But then these people weren't eligible for Social Security.
So it's just that's a big hardship for them.
I saw another one where someone got 10 11 million dollars from the state of California.
What sort of that's what I was most interested I guess is what sort of support do these states
provide the people that come out and why and why is it so far ranging.
Right yeah.
That's a really good question and it's a complicated answer because most states provide absolutely
nothing for exonerees immediately upon release.
And as opposed to somebody who committed the crime and gets released on parole that person
will have support state support from parole officers and and other ways.
But an exoneree typically gets nothing until he or she successfully litigates a civil compensation
suit.
So that's a separate litigation.
So you have you know all of your litigation in the criminal case is geared towards vacating
the conviction.
If you want any kind of state or federal compensation and those state statutes are all different
and they're different things you have to show to get state compensation versus federal compensation.
But you have to engage in a completely typically not every single state but typically you have
to engage in a separate civil litigation which again can be another one two three four years
until you see any money.
And if you do the range of that financial award as you just mentioned is significant.
So some states have a specific amount per year of wrongful incarceration.
Some do not some have a cap.
Some you have to show you have to prove innocence to a higher standard of proof than you even
had to in the criminal court.
So the compensation litigation is very complicated and not necessarily equitable.
Gotcha.
Well that's sad.
I mean I guess what it sounds like is this you talk to this new organization that's comprised
of people who were wrongfully convicted.
Is that a potential place for someone to go to work and make a living as part of that
as part of that program.
Well we have so at Life After Justice we have a branch of our nonprofit that is geared specifically
towards reentry of exonerees.
So to helping exonerees meet the many needs that they have upon reentry from incarceration.
You know those needs can be mental health.
That's what we focus on at Life After Justice.
But there's also just basic needs.
When you've been incarcerated for that long you need you need an ID.
You need a driver's license.
You need health insurance.
You need a job.
You need a place to live.
You need all these things immediately.
And there's a huge need for both you know innocence programs.
Most innocence programs attempt to help their clients with that.
And at BC we partner with the BC School of Social Work.
So we have social work students who are pursuing a masters help us draft our clients reentry
plans and then assist them with those needs.
But that's that's a big part of innocence work that I think the public often isn't
aware of how many needs exonerees have after they're released from prison.
Yeah.
You mentioned students working with you.
How much of the innocence network is made up of legal students doing these sorts of
projects?
A lot.
I mean like I said each each innocence organization is different.
But I think I would say I mean certainly the three that I've worked with closely and I
would venture to guess most of them involve law student help to some extent or volunteer
help.
Many are not running actual legal clinics like we are where our students at BC are with
us for an entire academic year over 20 hours a week and they're receiving class credit
for that.
So we have a significant amount of our resources our students and I think some projects probably
use students a lot less.
But I think that they all involve law students or nearly all involved law students to some
degree.
That's great.
I guess from the perspective of a current high school student in the Concord area how
would they end up getting involved with the innocence network as a career if they want
to become a lawyer?
That's a good question.
I would say you know reach out to the innocent if you go on the network website the innocence
network website you can sort it geographically so you can see the projects in your area.
In Massachusetts we have three so we have the New England Innocence Project, the BC
Innocence Program and the Committee for Public Counsel Services has an Innocence Program.
But you can search it geographically and contact information for all the projects is on that
website and I've had a number of you know Concord, Carlisle high school students, graduates
and while in high school reach out to me for internships or questions and I think that
a lot of people can get involved that way.
One final question from the perspective of somebody digging this up in 50 years for the
300th anniversary where would you like to see our legal system go in the next 50 years
what can happen that would make you happy?
Wow that is a loaded question.
Yeah come here for the big ones.
Wow okay I think that I would like to see a shift overall to prioritizing truth and
justice over finality and having a higher standard of proof for convictions and a willingness
for prosecutors and defense attorneys particularly post conviction but somewhat pretrial to
be less adversarial and more collaborative in finding the most just solution for that
particular crime victim and defendant.
Great answer well handled.
Good lawyer thinking on her feet.
Well thanks again for joining me and this has been a very educational week for me and
it's been really cool you know you've been a friend for a while and just being able to
see more of what you do with your career is incredible and a ton of respect for you.
Thanks again.
Good afternoon.