Alright, welcome to Concord Storytellers and making a return visit this time, Richard Smith,
local historian, Henry David Thoreau expert.
And we were talking and thought it'd be a lot of fun to dive deep on something we touched
upon briefly in the Thoreau episode.
And that was just what were people like in Concord in the 1850s, 175 years ago.
And it turned out Thoreau himself had written journals about his everyday interactions with
people, his everyday goings on.
People were different in a lot of ways in the 1850s, but people were also similar in
a lot of ways in that they were just doing their jobs every day, talking to neighbors,
seeing what people were up to, gossiping a little bit, talking trash about some people.
So I found it, I wouldn't say it's my favorite book I've ever read, but it has a solid 3.5
on Goodreads out of five stars.
I think that's appropriate.
It's a good book.
But it's interesting.
And for those of you that are wondering what book we're talking about, it's called Men
of Concord.
And it came out way after Thoreau died.
Thoreau died in 1862.
This book came out in 1936 and was actually the brainchild of N.C. Wyeth, the artist.
He loved Thoreau.
He was obsessed with him.
You could say that Thoreau was his spirit animal.
And so he always wanted to do some kind of a book about Thoreau, maybe using journal
entries and illustrating it.
And he started thinking about this like in 1918.
But it didn't happen until about 1930, 1934, when an editor at Houghton Mifflin named Francis
Allen, who had worked on Thoreau's journals in 1906, he got together with N.C. Wyeth and
said, let's do this book.
So he chose the journal entries that was going to go into this book.
Wyeth did the illustrations for the book.
And it came out in 1936.
And to a lot of Thoreauvians, yeah, it's kind of it's Henry kind of dish in the dirt and
talking about the people he knew, the famous people, the not so famous people.
And his journal is wonderful.
If you just read it, it's like an everyday snapshot of Concord in the mid 19th century.
And so what Wyeth and Allen did was they kind of got what they thought was the best little
bits from Thoreau's journal.
And they put it into this book in 1936.
Yeah.
And I think the more time goes on, the more interesting it gets, right?
Because the more everyday culture diverges from what it was like in the 1850s.
Absolutely.
And we were talking about before about how, at least from my perspective, growing up,
history is always very nobelized.
These noble virtues and these great historic things that happens tends to be a very serious
topic when you're talking about history.
Sure.
And the presidents and senators and generals and leaders and great men, of course.
You're not talking about what Chris Johnson and Richard Smith's of the day were doing
every day in their lives.
And I mentioned too that I think about 20 years ago, there was an ancient Greece and
Rome exhibit, the MFA.
And this switch just clicked in me when I saw I got past all of the weapons and all
that and I saw graffiti from ancient Rome and I saw a weapon from ancient Greece, but
it was a stone that was meant for a slingshot and it had written in Greek on it, eat this.
And I just thought, that's cool that people had, they had humor, they had jealousy, they
had all these emotions that we have, of course.
You would figure they do, but to see it put into context of those times is really interesting.
And I thought that a good way to do this would be to just go through some of our favorite
passages in this book.
And again, to reiterate, in Thoreau's time, if he had published this right as he was writing
these things, this is like me showing you my journal and saying, I did a Starbucks run
today.
I played nine holes of golf.
Well, it's like Facebook.
Yeah, exactly.
You go on Facebook and you see the minutia of everybody's lives.
Oh, we saw the black bear in the neighborhood this week.
I mean, that's exciting.
That is exciting today.
But a lot of this stuff is just going to go right over your head, but as time goes by,
it'll become more interesting.
And I wonder 175 years from now what people will think about us.
And they say, okay, there's some everyday things they did, but those barbarians used
to eat animals or something like that.
I can't believe they used chemotherapy.
What was wrong with these people?
Yeah, I mean, just there's going to be stuff that makes us look barbaric.
Well, it's interesting because about about 20 years, not even after Thoreau died, there
were some people who are actually interested in maybe publishing selections from his journals.
And people went around Concord asking, well, you know, would you be interested in reading
Thoreau's journals?
And the famous story is one of Concord's town leaders said, why would anybody want to read
that stuff?
I mean, who really cares?
You know, and so here it is 100 years later, 150 years later.
And for me in particular, I probably read Thoreau's journals more than I read the stuff
that was published while he was alive.
You're getting the real person.
I mean, we're so lucky from the 19th century, all of these people, Emerson Thoreau, Margaret
Fuller, whomever you're talking about, Bronson Alcott, they all kept journals.
And it's the daily minutiae that that as a historian that I really like, because especially
when it comes to Thoreau, it really brings him alive.
You see what he likes, you see what he didn't like.
He and Emerson would sometimes get bitchy about each other in their journals.
And he would talk about people that he knew, people he didn't know.
And you like I said, you really get this little snapshot of mid 19th century Concord.
Yeah, exactly.
It animates that very stuffy portrait that you see of Thoreau and Emerson, for instance.
I do want to offer a disclaimer that we're not skipping anything here.
Not all of this is going to be PG.
It's from the 1850s, so it's not it's not going to be anything as near as shocking as
you can read in 2024.
But we're just going to go through and read some of our favorite snippets and react to
them.
We haven't shared with each other which snippets we bookmarked, but I thought we would just
go through and see some of them.
And I know that you've known these stories for a long time, but they were new to me.
So there are some pretty, pretty cool and shocking stuff in there, including the smack
talk and quite a bit about everyday hygiene in the 1850s.
That shocked me.
Yeah, well, can you find that one?
And we will you can read it and we'll talk a little bit about that because, yeah, by
the mid 19th century, they weren't as fastidious as we are today.
Nowadays we tend to be overly sanitized.
And that's that's not something you can say about people who were living in the mid 19th
century or even before.
Yeah, I think I might have to get to that one a little bit.
My bookmarking technique here was basically just scrap paper and I have to go I have to
go in kind of chronological order through the book.
Oh, sure.
Let's do that.
Why don't we just go back and forth with some of our favorite passages and I'll start
early in the book around page 17.
They liked a good fire back in the day.
And there's an entire passage here.
June, June 4, 1850 said, Today I've been tending a burning in the woods.
Ray was there.
There's a pleasant fact that you will know no man long, however low and social scale,
however poor, miserable, and temperate and worthless he may appear to be a mere burden
to society.
But you'll find at least that there is something in which he understands and can do better
than any other.
And getting into that he's maybe not a fan of Ray.
I was pleased to hear that one man had sent Ray as the one had had the most experience
in setting fires of any man in Lincoln.
He had experience and skill as a burner of brush.
So great admiration for a man who can set a good fire.
Well, it's funny because that that was an important thing to know how to do.
You had to have somebody who knew to do things like that.
There's another journal entry where Thoreau talks about his mom and she remembers growing
up over on the Virginia road and she would hear a neighbor from a long distance away
whistling and he was known in Concord as being an admirable whistler.
So yes, you've got the admirable whistler.
You've got this guy who's the admirable burner of brush.
There's another guy that Thoreau writes about how he was really good at slaughtering pigs.
You know, they've all got these little things about them that sets them apart.
So you see the guy walking down the street you're like, well, that's the burner of brush
over there.
I mean, it seems in these days there aren't there's not a massive AT&T, GE, Google, Apple,
where you have thousands of people working at these companies.
People have very specific skills and trades.
And I feel like that that came out to me as people admired someone who had mastered something,
however small that that skill may be.
Absolutely.
There were people in the 19th century.
You knew who the best cobbler was.
You knew who the best blacksmith was.
You knew the guy to go to if you needed a horse broken or something like that.
These were everyday skills.
And it's not like you went to school for any of this stuff.
I'm sure this guy didn't go to Harvard learning how to burn brush.
It was just something that he had done time and time and time again until he got really
good at it.
And Thoreau really admired those kind of things in the everyday people.
He liked the muskrat hunters and the brush burners and the people like that because he
liked the folks who had a trade.
They were using that trade.
They were making a living doing it.
And to him that was like good, honest, hard labor.
And he absolutely admired those kind of people.
That's cool.
What do you got from your first passage?
OK, so Thoreau briefly lived in New York City in 1843.
And when he was there, he became friends with Horace Greeley, the editor of the New York
Tribune.
And after Thoreau came back to Concord, Greeley was always trying to get him to write about
the famous people that he knew.
He's like, look, you know Emerson, you know Hawthorne, you know Bronson Alcott.
If you write essays about these guys, I will publish them and get them published for you.
And Thoreau, he wanted nothing to do with it.
But he did write stuff in his journal.
And I tend to think that these are pieces that he was jotting down for possible publication.
So this is from sometime between 1845 and 47 about Ralph Waldo Emerson.
Emerson again is a critic, poet, philosopher with talents not so conspicuous, not so adequate
to his task, but his field is still higher, his task more arduous.
Lives a far more intense life, seeks to realize a divine life, his affections and intellect
equally developed.
He has advanced farther and a new heaven opens to him.
Love and friendship, religion, poetry, the holy are familiar with him.
The life of an artist, more observing, not so robust, elastic, practical enough in his
own field, faithful, a judge of men.
More of the divine realized him than in any.
A poetic critic reserving the unqualified nouns for the gods.
So he's obviously jotting down, it's very free form, almost like he's just kind of writing
down what he thinks about Emerson.
He did the same thing for Bronson Alcott, but he never had those things published.
He's kind of toying with the idea.
And this was 1845, 1847, about the time that he was living at Walden.
He probably wrote this when he was at Walden.
He still is getting along with Emerson.
They were still very good friends.
And you can see in this young, he was like about 28 to 30 when he's writing this.
And he's still kind of enamored by his friendship with this guy.
Here's this guy who's letting me live on his land at Walden Pond and he's this amazing
person.
Right.
So he's, modern day publications, he's writing about Emerson for the New Yorker.
And he gets the TMZ.
Right, exactly.
Exactly.
Yeah, this isn't quite the dirt yet.
And then a little bit later in his life, to continue that thread.
So in 1858, Emerson and a bunch of other writers and philosophers went to the Adirondacks for
a couple of weeks.
And they were camping and hunting and stuff like that.
And Thoreau thought it was absolutely ridiculous.
And so from 1858, he writes in his journal, Emerson says, this is from August 23rd, 1858,
Emerson says that he and Agassi and company broke some dozens of ale bottles, one after
another with their bullets in the Adirondack country, using them for marks.
Think of Emerson shooting a Pee-Wee for Agassi and cracking an ale bottle with his rifle
at six rods.
So he's just amazed that Emerson is out there shooting guns in the Adirondacks.
And he finds it finds it to be absolutely ridiculous.
I love to hear it.
So I want to get so I think showing that he had the ability to trash talk a little bit
eight years prior in 1850, he describes he seems to have a fascination a bit with drunk
people, a drunken Dutchman.
It's a good story.
It's a good story writing about drunk Dutchman.
Yeah.
And I just I'll read it's a long passage.
I'll just read a snippet from it.
He says, I was less disgusted.
I was less disgusted by their filthiness and vulgarity because I was compelled to look
at them as animals, as swine in their stye.
For the whole voyage, they lay flat on their backs on the bottom of the boat and Bilgewater
and wet with each bailing, half insensible and walling in their own vomit.
So admiration, disgust, what are we feeling here from from his his description of the
drunk Dutchman?
So thorough was a bit of a prude when it came to drinking and stuff like that.
It's funny because a lot of times when I'm talking to older, older folks who grew up
in the 60s, they say stuff like, oh, I'd love to sit at Walden Pond with thorough and smoke
a joint.
Yeah.
And I'm like, yeah, you're totally barking up the wrong tree with this guy.
But thorough, he he was kind of a prude when it came to to drunkenness, to bad behavior,
to people who were acting less, who were acting pretty uncouth.
And that's what he saw in these people.
Yeah, he's kind of turned off by and disgusted by this.
There's another instance where he was going to, I think, down to Hingham on a boat.
And there were young Irish boys who were smoking and swearing and being really loud and obnoxious.
And he writes in his journal, I thought of infanticide among the Chinese with some complacency.
And he was completely appalled that these 12 year old kids were smoking and being really
rude.
He thought it was disgusting.
So I think it really bothered him when he would see people not living on the higher
plane that he expected of human beings to do.
You know, here's thorough, who's kind of living this life.
He's trying to always be the best person that he can be and live on a higher level of consciousness.
And he sees things like this.
He's thinking, God, what's wrong with these people?
He feels a bucket.
He absolutely did.
Yeah, sure.
Yeah.
And he's kind of a prude New Englander.
OK.
And our reputation is well earned and steeped in long tradition.
Absolutely.
And so he sees people not acting the way he thinks people should act.
And it really bothers him when people are put down to the level of, what did he say,
animals?
Yeah.
He wasn't disgusted by them because he didn't view them as human.
He viewed them as animals.
Yeah.
And he's very prude, very judgmental.
And you just want to be like, dude, mind your own business.
Yeah.
I mentioned I'm going to do two because this one is kind of related in terms of people
being.
Well, this one is actually something that's directed at him.
But there's this visitors to the Walden hut, January 17, 1852.
And it seemed like I noticed that it seemed like it was a thing to do during these times
to just stop by somebody's house, even if you didn't know them and just ask for water.
There's no Starbucks runs.
Right.
Yeah.
So you just stop by and ask for water.
And he said, I don't have any cold water, but I lent them a dipper, which I don't know
if it's like a ladle, like a ladle.
So we could go maybe go to the river or pond or whatever and grabs some water.
Yeah.
Well, it turned out that they didn't even really want water.
They just wanted to steal the dipper.
So they just ran off with it.
Were these the two women?
The two women, the two young women.
Yeah.
Sure.
You know this story.
Yeah.
He was appalled.
He was appalled that these two women borrowed the dipper and they disappeared with it.
Yeah.
And they never came back, which, you know, when he was living at Walden pond, it kind
of became the thing.
Let's go down and see what this guy is doing down there.
And so unfortunately, these two women are lost to history.
We don't know if they were Concordians.
Maybe they were visiting Concord and somebody said, oh, you should go down and see the hermit,
quote unquote, of Walden pond.
But yeah, they stole his dipper.
So they might have just been playing a prank on him or something.
Could have been doing that.
It was like almost there.
Maybe they were dared to go.
Absolutely.
To steal something from the hermit or whatever.
There's another instance where he was living at Walden pond.
There was an instance where there were a couple of young men who had a young girl with them
at the pond.
And he doesn't go into a lot of detail, but you're under the impression that these boys
were trying to take advantage of this young lady.
And thorough really went off on these guys and basically yelled at him and made them
go away.
So he was defending this young lady's honor.
Oh, very noble.
What a chivalrous guy he was.
But yeah, there's all these weird little things like this, all these weird little stories
happening when he's at Walden pond.
These women steal the dipper.
Doesn't he say, he says something really nasty about him afterwards, if I'm not mistaken.
Yeah, he did.
I lost the mark.
But basically he says something along the lines of, I mean, what he's saying is basically,
they should have known better and they'll rue the day or something.
I'll find my revenge.
Right, yeah.
Or they're going to end up feeling guilty about it and I hope they realize what a bad
thing they've done.
So yeah, so again, Henry being kind of judgmental, but they stole his dipper.
And remind us how old he is at this time.
When he moved to Walden, he was about to turn 28 and he left when he was 30.
It's a little young to be in the get off my lawn stage of life.
A little young to be in that stage of life, but he's also, here's the guy who's leading
this life that he thinks he's on a higher level.
And I'm not saying that to be snarky because he really felt like he was kind of trying
to better his life.
And when he sees people around him not doing that, it's when he got really disappointed
in mankind.
It really bothered him when he didn't see people living up to their potential.
Be they drunkards or girls stealing dippers or whatever.
What do you have next for me?
Let's see.
Oh yeah.
So his best friend was a poet named Ellery Channing.
And they were thick as thieves.
They went on walks together all the time.
They traveled together.
So this is from 1852.
Channing says he keeps a dog for society to stir up the air of the room when it becomes
dead for he experiences awful solitude.
Another time thinks we must cultivate the social qualities.
Perhaps I'd better keep two dogs a piece.
They did have a dog.
Channing had a dog.
They called it Professor because he was kind of stupid.
Other people in town called it Professor because they thought the dog was probably smarter
than Ellery or Henry.
But they said that they liked having the dog with them because they would walk out.
And it was a newfoundling.
So it was a fairly big dog.
But he would stir up quail and rabbits and stuff that they wouldn't have seen otherwise.
So that's why Thurow liked having the dog.
Although it should be said here and now that Thurow was not necessarily a dog person.
He was a cat person.
He wrote about cats.
And the Thurow family had lots of cats over the years.
He wrote about these cats all of the time.
That's classic cat person.
He is a classic cat person.
Sure.
He'd be posting the pictures of his cats on Facebook.
Absolutely.
He'd be the cat person on Facebook.
And he'd be sharing the cute cat videos on YouTube.
Oh yeah.
There's this one instance where the cat, I think it was the cat Min, there was a mouse.
And the cat was playing with a mouse.
And then the Thurow's rooster came along and grabbed the mouse and threw it up into the
air and swallowed it.
And he said that the cat looked around for a while wondering where did that mouse go.
He seemed really confused by the whole thing.
He probably talked about this for days.
Oh yeah.
I'm sure he did.
Yeah.
So yeah.
So Thurow was a cat person.
Cats would be all over his Facebook page.
Love it.
I mean I don't love it.
I'm not a cat person.
The more and more I'm hearing I'm thinking maybe Thurow wouldn't be my kind of guy to
hang out with.
I'm not sure if he would be my kind of guy to hang out with.
To tell you the truth.
I would like to watch him.
I would like to see him speak and maybe see him interact with other people.
But I'd also be afraid of just being a total idiot in front of him and saying something
that either he didn't agree with or.
I've known that in this life as well.
Just me being stupid.
You know I'd probably make some stupid joke and that would be the end of that relationship.
Never meet your heroes.
That's why you make your heroes dead people.
Absolutely.
I've been telling my heroes have been dead for 150 years.
So we previewed this in the beginning but I have gotten to the bathing section.
Oh good.
OK.
And I.
So some of these I'm going to read in my own words or just telling my own words and some
of them I'll read.
This one I got to read.
OK.
Because I think it's fantastic.
And it's July 8th 1852.
This is not long after the Dipper incident.
He says he talks about this like we talk about intermittent fasting or taking certain new
thing vitamins.
Right.
I'm inclined to think bathing almost one of the necessities of life but it is surprising
how indifferent some are to it.
What a coarse foul busy life we lead compared even with the South Sea Islanders in some
respects.
Truant boys steal away debate but the farmers who most need it rarely dip their bodies into
the streams or ponds and was telling me last night they had thought of bathing when he
had done his hoeing of taking some soap and going on the wall and giving himself himself
a good scrubbing.
But something had occurred to prevent it and now he'll go unwashed to the harvesting I
even until the next hoeing is over.
Pray what were rivers made for one farmer who came to bathe and walled in one Sunday
while I live there told me it was the first bath he had had for 15 years.
What kind of religion could his be or was it any better than a Hindu's.
Explain Richard.
OK.
So it's the mid 19th century bathing is not a daily occurrence for a lot of people or
annual in some cases.
Well because there's no running water at least not in Concord or in most places.
And so taking a bath was a pain in the rear end.
You'd have a tub of some sort.
You might keep it in the barn.
You might keep it in a spare room.
You'd have to pull the tub out.
You have to go out to the well get bucket after bucket of water heat up that water on
the stove put that water into the tub take your bath take that water out of the tub out
somewhere and dump it out.
If you've got a family of three four five six seven people that's a pain.
So bathing is not quite as common whole body bathing.
People would wash their face and hands on a daily occurrence.
That's pretty normal.
But the whole idea of bathing entirely it just didn't really occur to people because
it was just it was just a pain to do it.
And why.
You know there's also a popular concept at the time that a person's natural odors and
oils and everything that keeps you healthy.
If you're washing that stuff off then you're going to you're probably going to be susceptible
to disease of some sort.
Thoreau is not buying any of that when he's living at Walden Pond.
He was bathing almost every day.
Although he does write that he usually had his last bath about the middle of October
because the pond is frozen frozen.
Yeah.
So the all cuts were a little bit different.
They were actually into cold water bathing when they were living over at the hillside
on Lexington Road.
Bronson actually set up a cold water shower for the family.
They believed in bathing almost every day.
But that's definitely the exception rather than the rule in mid 19th century Concord.
And you know here's this farmer who had net a bath in 15 years.
Yeah.
And he was I'm not sure if he was proud of it.
He was just like well yeah.
Why would I.
Right.
I'm holding out because I'm being some martyr for.
Being fully natural.
It is why would I.
I also think that you know if you went back to the 19th century you're walking down Main
Street in Concord in 1852 there would have been a lot of smells.
Yeah.
I think all of these people would have smelled like wood smoke.
I think they would have all smelled a little bit like sweat.
I think they would have all smelled a little bit like if you're a farmer something not
so pleasant.
Yeah.
You know especially if you're shoveling muck and manure all day.
It's not.
It's not like they all walked around going oh look at me I stink.
I think it was just that was what it smelled like.
Just the way it was.
Right.
And you get used to it.
Probably just smelled like nothing.
Right.
It's like when you're cooking something in your kitchen and you're not really smelling
it because it's slowly coming onto you then you leave the room or you leave the house
for a minute you come back in and it just smells amazing.
Right.
Exactly.
That's the sensation that comes to you.
Yeah.
And there were people who you know there were perfumes and colognes and stuff like that.
At the time a lot of men were using hair oil which supposedly smelled pretty good.
So I think they were aware of it and there was a certain amount of cleanliness at least
some people were bathing once a week.
But they weren't washing their face and hands every day.
There was shaving going on and stuff like that.
We can be assured that if I get in a time machine and go back to this time and conquer
it and go into a tavern I will pass out.
You probably will.
Well and also you think about that you go into the tavern there's cigar smoke there's
pipe smoke.
That helps.
A little bit.
Yeah.
So yeah I think of that not wanting to meet your heroes.
You know I just imagine.
Well you know they talk about the Civil War how these guys just all smelled horrible.
Yeah.
Whole armies would march by and they said it was the smell would linger for days and
days.
Right.
So the 19th century was not a place for the faint of faint of smell.
Not my place.
No.
What do you got for me next.
Let's see what do we have.
Oh yeah.
This is a good one.
June 17th 1853.
Here have been three ultra reformers lecturers on slavery temperance the church etc. in our
house the last three or four days.
And then he talks about who these ministers are.
Excuse me.
They addressed each other constantly by their Christian names and rubbed you continually
with the greasy cheeks of their kindness.
They would not keep their distance but cuddle up in life spoon fashion with you no matter
how hot the weather or how narrow the bed.
He was talking about one of them in particular.
They lick you as a cow licks her calf.
They would feign rap you about with their bowels.
And one of them addressed me as Henry within one minute from the first I first from the
time I first laid eyes on him.
And when I spoke he said withdrawing sultry sympathy.
Henry I know all you would say I understand you perfectly.
You need not explain anything to me and to another.
I am going to dive into Henry's in most depths.
And I said I trust you will not strike your head against the bottom.
So they lay their sweaty hand on your shoulder or your knee and try to magnetize you.
So he's not impressed with these reformers these ministers that were staying at his mother's
boarding house for a few days.
He didn't he didn't take reformers he didn't take to so-called reformers very kindly if
it seemed like they were doing it either for the money or for the fame or for the notoriety.
Yeah.
And this is a really long journal entry.
One of them wrote a book and he said that you know he shocks all the old ladies with
his infidelities in this book.
So he thinks that these are guys these are like the televangelists of their day.
Sure.
And you know the type.
And when I read this journal entry those are the types I imagine.
Right.
Or the televangelists you see.
Yeah.
And they just seem so smarmy and so fake and so so slick.
He sees right through them.
And that's what these guys were.
And so he's completely turned off by him.
You know he was friends with people like William Lloyd Garrison and the Alkitts and Wendell
Phillips and other diehard abolitionists.
And he really believed in what they were doing.
But it's these kind of guys who are just like a dime a dozen that completely completely
threw him for a loop and he couldn't stand being anywhere near him.
Yeah.
Well it's funny you mentioned Garrison Phillips because I have some trash talk about them
as well as Harvard all in one sentence.
Oh great.
It's the trifecta.
Yeah.
This is Alcott and the Abolition Society.
So Alcott this is August 10th 1853.
Alcott had spent the day before at Emerson and came to visit him.
And basically it sounds like Alcott the it says the question of livelihood was troubling
him.
So what was he going to do to get paid.
What was he going to do to make a living.
And he offered his services to the Abolition Society to go out in the country to speak
for freedom but they declined him.
And he says this is very much to their discredit.
They should have been forward to secure him.
Such a connection with him would confer unexpected dignity on their enterprise but they cannot
tolerate a man who stands by a head above them.
So he obviously holds Alcott in higher regard than even these other people.
And this is this is the punch line.
Gareth is bad Garrison and Phillips etc. as the overseers and faculty of Harvard College.
They require a man who will train well under them.
Consequently they have not in their employ any but small men these trainers.
See that's he's slamming everything that was considered something you shouldn't slam.
You know you don't you know you don't say nasty things about Harvard especially if you're
a Harvard graduate.
You know you know you've got these men these great men.
And he did like Phillips and Garrison but he obviously liked Alcott a lot more.
So thorough is one thorough and Emerson were two of the few people that stood by Bronson
Alcott no matter what.
You know he had a reputation and still has this horrible reputation for being lazy and
he's letting the little women starve and he's impractical and he's a much better talker
than he is a doer etc etc.
But in his day in their day Bronson really had a reputation for being a man who stood
by his convictions and was a diehard reformer and abolitionist.
And thorough and Emerson absolutely believed in him as a genius.
Emerson at one time called him a half god you know and couldn't believe that people
weren't taking him seriously.
But because he was a little impractical and he was a terrible writer and he seemed a little
bit like kind of like an absent minded crank at times.
People didn't really take him that seriously.
And so I think that what happened was Garrison and Phillips and the other abolitionists they
probably were afraid that Alcott's reputation would precede him.
So they're very serious and they're very intense and here's this guy who's kind of considered
kind of dreamy and kind of weird.
And they didn't want to they didn't want to be associated with that.
As much as they liked him.
They thought it would ruin the brand.
Absolutely.
But from what we understand everybody even his detractors really liked the man.
They thought he was kind and gentle and intense and serious and he believed 100 percent in
whatever it is he wanted to believe in his transcendentalism.
But on the other hand they don't really want to hang out with him and they don't really
want him to be part of the brand as you would say.
Which is interesting because there was an instance in 1854 when there was a runaway
slave in Boston Anthony Burns who was arrested and he was going to be sent back to slavery.
And there was this big riot in Boston at the old courthouse to try to save him.
And there were some gunshots and the crowd refused to go near the courthouse and only
one guy walked forward to try to save him and it was Bronson Alcott.
He walked across the plaza up the steps of the courthouse and he turned to the crowd
and he said why aren't we inside.
You know and to me that's like Bronson Alcott's greatest moment.
Because he's the only one even though he might have gotten shot who knows what could have
happened but he bravely and calmly walked across the courtyard up the steps of the courthouse
to say why aren't we going inside.
And to me this huge crowd of people are cowards and here's this guy this lone guy walking
across the courtyard.
So he was absolutely dedicated and so and Thoreau knew that.
Thoreau was like they're kind of missing out on having him with them.
He would have added a lot he thought.
Well I think I mean even in even today I've been part of many organizations boards committees
all these different all these different entities that perform actions.
And I would say that it still remains true that there are many different types of thinking
in this world and that people who are very lenient tend to be more linear very organized
people who have a message they're sticking to it that someone who's more maybe more this
more dreamy creative scattering person while interesting and full of ideas maybe is someone
they don't quite understand or they're almost like dangerous to them because they don't
know where they're going to go.
And they might say our organization is about this very specific thing this is exactly what
we're going for and this person might take us off might take us off of that mission.
Right and the transcendentalist whether it was Emerson or Thoreau or Bronson Alcott they
all kind of had I'm not going to say it was their reputation but it's what a lot of more
mainstream people thought of them.
Yeah you know they thought Thoreau was this weird hermit living in the woods by himself
who who was just kind of communing with nature.
Yeah they thought Bronson Alcott was this dreamy idealist and they all had this reputation
which kind of lasted even up until today.
I still talk to lots of people who they think all Thoreau did was live at Walden Pond and
grow beans and he didn't really do anything.
You know except sit around and be judgmental.
Yeah a bit of that.
Absolutely you know it's it's kind of it's kind of interesting that yeah Thoreau was
incredibly judgmental if you read him that way but I also think that he was he was just
he's just trying to help you man.
He's just trying to trying to get you through your daily grind.
Yeah yeah you know and he's trying to give you advice and he even says in Walden he says
I would have no man adopt my mode of living on any account.
So I've got a good one.
Let's do it.
This this just this is just so weird.
July 25th 1853 I have for years had a great deal of trouble with my shoestrings because
they get untied continually.
They are leather rolled and tied in a hard knot but some days I could hardly go 20 rods
before I was obliged to stop and stoop to tie my shoes.
My companion and I speculated on the distance to which one tying would carry you the length
of a shoe tie and we thought it nearly as appreciable and certainly a more simple and
natural measure of distance than a league or mile.
Ever in a non we raised our feet on whatever fence or wall or rock or stump we chance to
be passing and drew the strings once more pulling as hard as we could.
It was very vexatious when passing through low scrubby bushes to become conscious that
the strings were already getting loose again before we had barely started.
What should we have done if we were pursued by a tribe of Indians.
So it goes on and on and on and on and at last the other day it occurred to me that
I would try an experiment and instead of tying two simple knots one over the other the same
way putting the end which fell to the right over each time that I would reverse the process
and put it under the other.
Gratly to my satisfaction the experiment was perfectly successful and from that time my
shoestrings have given me no trouble except sometimes in tying them at night.
On telling this to others I learned that I had been all the while tying what is called
a granny's knot but now I had blundered into a square knot.
Should not all the children be taught this accomplishment and devoted to instruction
in tying knots.
So Henry's walking around for years with his laces coming undone and then this is 1853
he's 35 years old and he figures out how to tie a square knot.
Wow that's I just find that so absolutely hilarious and so bizarre.
I and the fact that he's so fascinated and writes in such detail about it he's really
proud of it.
Yeah he blundered onto a square knot so of course I do living history as thorough and
years and years ago and ever since I've been doing Henry I've always tied my shoes as thorough
into a square knot and years and years ago I was doing a gig at the Concord Museum and
this woman came up to me and she was always kind of a smart aleck and always trying to
get me to break character and she said so if you're Henry thorough show me your shoelaces
and so I showed her my shoelaces and of course they were tied into a square knot and I said
they're tied in a square knot of course and she was like damn it.
She's going to get you.
So yeah so if you ever see me as thorough you will see my shoes tied in a square knot.
Does Richard Smith tie his shoes in a square knot?
I do not.
No I don't go that far because I agree with him because they're leather shoelaces and
at times when I'm done being Henry they're hard to untie.
I get it I feel Henry's pain when it comes to shoelaces.
All right well I have two more and one is two very short ones together but it's and
the first one is actually related to clothing as well but these are both just everyday observations
that he seemed to find really funny.
This first one reminds me of how in Shakespearean times when they would do plays that they would
find the weirdest things hilarious like if someone came out and mismatched socks it would
make the crowd go wild.
So he says February 19th 1857 an old man one of my neighbors is so demented that he put
both legs into one leg of his pantaloons the other morning exclamation point he doesn't
use many exclamation points so clearly he was he's amazed by this.
The next one everyday observation.
But is that it?
That's it.
But he's found it crazy enough that he was going to write it down.
March 11 1859.
E. Hosmer says that a man told him that he had seen my uncle Charles take a 12 foot ladder
set it up straight then run up and down the other side kicking it from behind him as it
went down.
E. H. told of seeing him often at the tavern toss his hat to the ceiling twirling it over
and catch it on his head every time.
So kind of stupid human tricks.
That's exactly what they are.
Yeah from back in the day.
Well see and it's those kind of stories that Thoreau loved to put into his journal because
these are the little weird bizarre things that that people are talking about in the
streets of Concord.
Yeah.
Did you see did you see the guy with the ladder.
It was the craziest thing he ran up and then kicked it down and went down to the other side.
Right and I'm sure the magician and I'm sure the guy putting his pants his legs in the
same pantaloons I'm sure that one are all around town.
Yeah.
Does he say does he say if he saw it or if he heard it.
He said he saw it.
OK.
Yeah.
But I'm sure he told everybody well everyone you wouldn't believe what I saw.
Exactly.
I have one last good one.
Bring it.
OK.
So Uncle Charles Dunbar his mom's brother lived with them with the Thoreau family for
quite some time before he passed away.
January 1st 1853 after talking with Uncle Charles the other night about the worthies
of this country Daniel Webster and the rest as usual considering who were geniuses and
who were not.
I showed him up to bed and when I had got into bed myself I heard the chamber door open
after eleven o'clock and he called out in an earnest stentorian voice loud enough to
wake the whole house.
Larry was John Quincy Adams a genius.
No I think not was my reply.
Well I didn't think he was answered he.
And that was it.
So those are the kind of conversations he and he and Uncle Charles are having.
Well for bedtime.
The last one I had and this is I don't know my head at this out but I just I have to know
if 15 year old me is thinking along the right lines.
This is where we're going off PG and you might want to go earmuffs if you're listening to
this if you might be offended.
But this is something Henry wrote so I want to cover it.
So August 11th 1852 Alcott was here the ninth and tenth.
He had been to his native town of Walcott Connecticut and on this errand faithfully
peruse the records of some 15 towns read the epitaphs and as many churchyards and wherever
he found the name Alcock excerpted it and all connected with it for he was delighted
to discover that his original name was all cock and meant something that his grandfather
or great grandfather bore it.
Philip Alcock though his son wisely changed it to Alcott.
So he changed his name.
Did he change it for the reason that I think that I changed it for.
Yes so spelled A L C O C K.
Yes that was those are the ancestors of Bronson Alcott.
So his his name which probably was originally all cock all cock but was probably when it
was first formulated way back in the day.
Right.
Didn't mean anything salacious right.
A slang term comes out and his name all of a sudden becomes hilarious and they decide
they're going to change it.
Is that how I'm reading that.
Is that what I think you're reading it exactly right.
Barrow says that they wisely changed it.
Yeah and and that's that pretty much coincides with the way that Bronson and Louisa's name
is pronounced.
So most people say Louisa May Alcott.
Yep.
But years ago when I was working at Orchard House the home of Louisa I was being trained
I had only been in Concord a short time I was being trained to be a tour guide there
and I gave this great tour to to Jan Turingquist who is still the director there and I was
saying Alcott Alcott Alcott and at the very end of the tour Jan said you did a great job
but it's all kit which would go with the change all cock.
Yeah.
So those of you if you're having a hard enough time getting used to saying Henry Thoreau's
name as Henry David Thoreau you now have to start pronouncing it Bronson and Louisa Alcott.
It's getting tough man.
I know it's a whole conquered thing.
You got to learn how to speak like these people.
Concord thing.
Don't get me started on Peabody.
OK.
Well that that I that I had from Tennessee actually called the Peabody.
Oh.
I don't know instead of lot it was Lafayette Tennessee instead of Lafayette.
It's this way.
But anyway I think there's a Versailles in Indiana or Illinois.
But anyway so yes Thoreau as in I do a thorough job and Louisa May all kit like a CUT right.
Yeah.
L.L.C.T.
Yes.
Cool.
Well this has been a lot of fun.
I I did enjoy reading the book and I thought I learned a lot and I how lucky am I that
I get a chance to talk to you about it to add further context.
This is these stories I'm reading and this is my life.
This is what I do.
I read these things and I try to figure out what he's talking about and do research in
other areas too because a lot of times he's he's kind of he's not as detailed as he should
be.
Yeah.
And so you got to figure out what especially when he writes spent the day with E.H.
And you're like well who who the hell's that.
Yeah.
And you got to figure out who E.H. was or whomever.
So you know Henry's journals are a great place to start.
I think if you want to get a really good sense of what Concord was like in the mid 19th century.
Outstanding.
Well I'm glad we did this and I continue to learn more every week and get to know more
about my now hometown of Concord.
You're learning a lot.
You're getting the crash course.
Thank you Mr. Smith and hopefully we can do this again.
My pleasure.
Thank you very much.