Okay, this is Concord Storytellers and today another special guest, friend, neighbor, scientist,
father, Micah Benson. Welcome. Hi CJ. Thanks for joining. Today we're going to talk about,
and we kind of pregame this, about talking about COVID-19 from the perspective of telling somebody
50 years from now about it. So what was it like going through that from a few different lenses,
one as a scientist, another as just a human locking down, another from the parent's perspective,
and we may find a couple others along the way. But even when we were just kind of previewing,
doing this episode together, it was amazing how many memories it kind of buried already
from four or five years ago. And so it's been interesting digging this back up, obviously a
pretty dark time in the world, a lot of unknowns that aren't all completely solved yet, but
something that would be interesting to talk about and you being an expert in the field,
I thought it would be really interesting to talk to you and bring that perspective in
and just talk about how you perceived it during the time that it was all going on. So welcome.
Could you just talk a bit about yourself and your career?
Yeah, absolutely. So thanks CJ and glad to be here. So first off, when I was thinking about this,
I realized that this was probably going to be the least viewed podcast, at least for individuals
within Concord today, in large part because no one wants to remember what happened in COVID.
Yeah. I think we've all collectively buried it. And at least for me, I don't pretend to be an
expert vaccinologist or epidemiologist, but what I am is an immunologist. So I trained
as a cellular immunologist, I did my PhD in it. I trained at Dartmouth, did a postdoc at Harvard,
and I think as it relates to my perspective during COVID, I actually did my PhD on humoral memory,
which is what happens when you encounter a pathogen, whether it's a virus or a bacteria,
your immune system recognizes it, and then it develops a immunological memory immune response.
And in particular, what I studied was one of the confounding questions that I think still persists
is why do memory responses against vaccines, against pathogens, stick around for the lifetime
of the individual? I think we now know that there's certainly a lot of nuance to that,
at least with COVID. One of the unfortunate things was that I think we learned kind of the hard way
that some of the durability of the vaccines kind of waned after six, nine months, which led to a
need for boosters. So there's certainly exceptions to that, but at least during my PhD, I studied,
I'm going to identify some of the survival factors as to what keeps the cell type that produces
antibodies against pathogens alive. Yeah. Interesting. Yeah. I'll say,
I find myself surrounded by Dartmouth alums. Is there like some sort of thing there where you
move to Metro West, Massachusetts? Yeah. It's the trees.
Okay. Well, gotcha. Okay. Yeah. You get accustomed to it being in the New Hampshire and Northwoods.
And then you come to Boston and like a lot of people, you do your thing in the city,
then you slowly start getting that itch for trees and nature. And Dartmouth is a fantastic
destination to get that. And I would say there's actually a lot of similarities and feel between
downtown Concord as well as Hanover, where Dartmouth is. Cool. Yeah. I had similar vibes
looking out here from where I grew up in Tennessee. So I'm glad we all converse here. It's a great
community. So I wanted to say, I don't know of anybody in my life who had ever experienced a
pandemic before. I did a bit of research on this and Wikipedia has a really interesting article
about just a list of epidemics and pandemics and just how devastating they were. And it's
interesting, the Spanish flu is the most famous one that we believe likely killed around 100
million people. COVID is actually fifth currently. And the ranges are, it says seven to 35 million
just because I think it's just very difficult, especially with a new disease, to say that this
was the exact cause of death or a severe illness as opposed to something else, a comorbidity that
was going on. I learned that word during the pandemic as well. And then something I texted
you about earlier today, there's this 1545 to 1548 coccolisitis epidemic, or epidemic, it wasn't
pandemic, so it didn't go across continent, but it took out up to 80% of the Mexican population.
Yeah. I just wanted to put that out as a frame of reference that there are viruses, there are
organisms in this world that are that lethal, that if they were spreading, that if they were
spread quickly, that it could be that devastating to a population. And my understanding is that
early on in COVID, we had no idea whether this was going to be something that passed quickly.
It's certainly spreading, but we didn't know how quickly it was spreading and we didn't know how
devastating it would be. Could you talk a bit about that and just kind of explain what it was
and where the scientific mindset was and how it evolved over time?
Yeah, sure. And to be fair, when you texted me the name of that epidemic that happened in Mexico,
which I great job pronouncing it, I'm not even going to try, I never heard of it either. It just
wasn't on my radar. And we all know about the 1918 influenza pandemic. I think it was a bit of a
misnomer. It was called the Spanish flu. It turns out it actually originated in Kansas. But that was
always the benchmark that I think kept scientists up at night, public health officials. So when I,
this is a bit of an anecdote, but when I was in college, I graduated in 2003 and I took a
microbiology course during my senior year. And about two weeks into the course, there started
emerging a number of influenza-like cases in Asia, in China. And it turns out that this was
kind of the opening salvo of SARS-1. And our professor at the time kind of recognized the
opportunity, put the syllabus down, and we started basically learning microbiology just by tracking
SARS-1 in real time. And very quickly, we were able to track the spread of China. I think there
are a couple other Asian countries. It made its way to Canada as well. It eventually killed around
800 people worldwide. There are a few very important, I think, numbers that I think we
were following as a benchmark. So for influenza, back in 1918, it killed, I mean, well into the
double digits, numbers of individuals that infected. I want to say the mortality rate was
well into the 30s, maybe the 40s. I don't remember the exact number. At least for SARS-1,
at least for SARS-1 that emerged in 2003, 2004, the mortality rate was around 10%.
And that's also very high. And I think that that kept people up at night, certainly. Now,
I think one of the reasons why it didn't spread more broadly was the fact that every patient that
had SARS-1 was symptomatic. There were very few asymptomatic patients. And it could only
transmit the virus if you were symptomatic. So it was actually relatively straightforward to
contain it. If you were sick, you'd undergo quarantine, and they're able to kind of build
a wall around the virus for that reason. So when was sick and they got sick
relatively quickly after catching it? Yeah. And even then, they had a pretty high mortality rate.
So there was another coronavirus that came out in 2010, I think the 2012, called MERS,
Middle Eastern Respiratory Virus, that had a higher risk of mortality. I think the vector there was
camels. But it was actually very hard to transmit. The person-to-person transmission was quite tough.
So it really hasn't spread that much, even though there is still, I think, outbreaks every so often.
So when this first emerged, I think the first cases started coming out in the news in Wuhan
and China in December. I think what we knew was there's influenza-like symptoms. It was relatively
quickly identified as a coronavirus, which is, to be quite frank, a known entity. Like I think-
So a common cold virus, right? Exactly. And it's actually, from a genetic standpoint,
relatively similar to SARS-1 and MERS. So you could study it at a culture. It was sequenced
pretty quickly. It had relatively high homology, actually, to SARS-1. So it was a known entity.
But I think it was very apparent that it also acted very differently. And one of the reasons
why was it just spread like wildfire. It was unknown how far it was spreading initially,
certainly first within China, in a particular year. And I think that it was not known why it
was spreading, whether it was due to fomines being spread on surfaces, or whether there was
a certain degree of asymptomatic spread. But I think it was probably in late December, early January
when China- In 2019, right? Yeah, exactly. What I think stood a lot of health officials up in their
chairs was the fact that China decided to lock down. It's like, OK, something serious is here.
Yeah. You need to start taking this seriously. And we started seeing it, some of the early cases,
I read actually the Biodenetorius Biogen Conference in Boston. I think New York Times reported late
in the year 2020 that around 300,000 people were infected just via that conference. That's an
insane number. Insane number. And I think it speaks to the fact that we got to that point. So
we knew something was brewing in Asia in beginning of 2020. And I think, I mean, correct me if I'm
wrong, we just went on with our lives. I don't think there was a lot of concern. This wasn't the
first time that something like this had popped up. I mean, I think over- I remember when I was a kid
and Ebola was a thing. And I was terrified that I was going to catch Ebola. But then I heard about
that. I heard about SARS, heard about mad cow disease, and all these scary sounding illnesses
popping up. But it's just out of sight, out of mind. I learned, I think a lot of us learned,
when this pops up, don't worry about it. It's not going to affect us. It almost felt like we had
this fortress here. Exactly. That prevented that we were as a population immune to these things.
So absolutely, I remember hearing about it. I remember seeing those images of the doctor
in the hospital bed. And he was saying, this is real. And we got to take this seriously.
And I was thinking, well, it's not going to come here. Yeah, exactly. And I think in January,
there was a lot, I mean, there was news for sure. And I think people were paying attention. But in
terms of editing our own lives, there was none of that. And even well into February, I think we're
like, okay, there's something going on over there, maybe not here. And you had a couple of
sporadic cases where you had an instance of someone traveling from the United States,
or sorry, from Asia over the United States, they would land, they were sick, and then they would
get tested. And then they were quarantined. But it was thought that, okay, that was an isolated
incident. And for me, there were probably two incidences that started getting me really nervous.
Almost even prior to the Biogen, the now famous Biogen conference that happened in March. One was
the, I think it was the Diamond Princess cruise ship. And it was, well, first an advertisement
not to take a cruise, unfortunately. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I've been on one. That's just because I get
motion sick. I don't even need a pathogen. But with this poor cruise ship in Asia,
in Asia, it basically just got slammed by COVID in the early days of the pandemic.
And what struck me, and I actually remember I was at work because I work in a biotech just surrounded
by a bunch of really smart people. And when this happened, we actually had lunch like, you know
what, we have a cruise ship. We know that based on the numbers that we're seeing, it's around 2%
mortality rate. We know that most of the people on this particular ship certainly have been exposed,
maybe, I forget the exact number, maybe half are infected. The curious thing was maybe half of
those people who tested positive were actually symptomatic, which means that there's a whole
lot of people that are asymptomatic. And what that means is unless you're incredibly, incredibly
diligent in testing, this virus is going to go everywhere just because you're not going to be
able to catch it. It's not going to be like the situation we had with SARS-1 where if you are
symptomatic, you could transmit it. But if you stopped someone who was symptomatic from being
exposing others, then you could stop it in its tracks.
Yeah. And it's sort of in like, I guess, lay terms that what we're kind of comparing here is
SARS-1, someone on a cruise ship somehow has it. They're really sick from the get-go. They're
isolating their cabin. They might not be shedding active virus or breathing it out or it might not
be contagious from the surface. There are many different properties of how contagious something
is, right? Like one virus, if we had 30 people in this basement, if I have one virus and we have
the same conversation, same mingling effect, I might infect one person. Another virus, I might
infect everybody in the room, just depending on how it acts. And we have no way, with something
new, no way to understand what that, is it the R0? Is that what it was called?
Yeah. I think a lot of people got a crash course in R0.
R0. Yeah. Absolutely.
And you try to benchmark, is it worse than measles? Is it better than measles?
Yeah. Yeah. And just trying to get it to, I think, trying to get it into terms that people
understand.
Yeah.
Yeah. And so I think the second event that happened in February that honestly scared me
was the fact that you had confirmed community transmission in Washington.
Yeah.
And I heard that, and it was confirmed that this person had not been exposed to, they hadn't
gone to Asia, they hadn't recently, they hadn't exposed to anyone who had recently gone to Asia.
Like, okay, it's definitely here. There's a lot of asymptomatic cases. And I think that's
why I was like, okay, buckle up time. And my wife was making fun of me because I think I told you
the story. I got a Costco membership that day, went out to Costco, dropped a whole lot of money
on a large chest freezer and a ton of food. I think my wife was saying, this is what immunologists
do when they nest. Yeah, absolutely. Well, I mean, I remember exactly March 17th. It was
St. Patrick's Day. It was the day Tom Brady said he was going to the box. It's already a pretty
devastating day. Yeah, that was a rough day. But that was the last day before we locked down for
what we thought was going to be two weeks. Did you buy two weeks?
No, no. I mean, so it was a time of incredible confusion, I think, even for people that
who otherwise kind of had like at least a working foundation in virology, immunology,
epidemics in general. So you mentioned the Biogen conference. So my wife was at that conference and
she actually met with a Biogen leadership team and she was directly exposed to those individuals. And
just to give you a sense of what it was like, I think she met with them on a Thursday and Friday.
She actually mentioned that, yeah, they look kind of sick. She comes home, the weekend passes. I
think we find out it may be a Sunday night that they had tested positive. And so we're looking at
each other like, what do we do next? Do I go to work? Do I stay home? Does life just carry on? Do
I only edit my life if I show symptoms? And we just did it now. She ended up staying home,
which was the right call and actually never went back to work, at least in person for a very long
time. And so at that time, there were a number of dominoes that were falling. You had Italy,
for example. I think we were seeing a lot of very, very scary images of Italy, where initially you
knew something was happening in China. Italy was the next country where it was a lot more real,
just because there was a lot more information that was coming out. I think there was,
you actually jog my memory on this, there was a famous story of a nurse who, I think there's
a picture of her. And was it a ventilator that she handed over to? Yeah. So there was a
elderly woman on a ventilator and they were out of ventilators, so they couldn't give them to
everybody who was a patient, who might need them. And there was a younger person in there and they
said, okay, well this younger person has a better shot at survival, just because they're younger.
And the elderly woman said, no. She said, I've had a beautiful life and I'd like you to give this to
her. And it's just like, it's heartbreaking. But I'm getting chills right now thinking about it,
because during this very confusing and dark time, you have these just like beautiful moments of
humanity happening as well. And even though it was a scary time, I did see in the news,
but also among my community, among my friends, like some just great acts of humanity among people.
And I really, some people were really shying during that time and helping people out. And
whether it was sacrificing your life like that, or whether it was just getting groceries for
somebody who's your neighbor who may be more at risk than you are. So it was part of the
dynamic of that time. Yeah, it was very strange because it was coming, I think everyone,
I think around early March or maybe mid-March, like everyone knew something big was about to happen.
It was clear that it was going to hit us, but no one really knew, A, how to prepare, well,
probably beyond buying food and stockpiling, stockpiling toilet paper. But in terms of how
to prepare beyond that, I think a lot of people were just kind of like, they were preparing for
something, but not quite knowing how. Yeah, 2074, if you're listening, for whatever reason,
there was a massive run on toilet paper. It was the first thing to go off the shelf. We ended up
having a lot of supply issues for a couple of years. Toilet paper was number one. I went
through the house. Once it hit me that this was serious, I went through the house. I was like,
I think we only have like six walls of toilet paper. We better get some. I went through the
house. It was 92. I was like, we're good. This is the least of our concerns. I ended up doing the
same thing you did. I have a massive freezer in my garage now full of protein, full of protein and
frozen vegetables. I had shelves down in the basement here with all kinds of non-perishable
stuff. My mom thought I... My wife probably thought I was crazy, but she was supportive of me
and how I was processing all this. My mom thought I had gone completely that shit.
I mean, I had heard anecdotes. I don't know who these people are, but it's one of those friends
of friends things where people had... They only exhausted their toilet paper stores well into
2022 that they had established in 2020, which is remarkable. I mean, lockdown was crazy. I mean,
kind of going through that process. Within a company where we were, we were trying to figure
out all the policies for our employees. What do we say? We didn't have national guidance yet.
Exactly. Then on the home front, you're thinking to yourself, well, apparently I need toilet paper,
so I got to stack up on that, but what about other stuff? What about kids? It was a time of just
unbelievable uncertainty, and yet there were still kind of trickets of normalcy as well because
things didn't lock down until they did. Even though a lot of people sense that something big
was coming up, I still have it ingrained in my memory. I was driving my daughter back from a
basketball game. I forget the name. I think it was Sudbury actually. We were listening on the radio,
listening on the news to the recent developments, and lockdown ultimately ended up happening two
days later. I just remember telling it, listen, we're about to go through some really historic
stuff. What's about to happen is going to hit us. It's going to hit us hard. You're going to
remember this for the rest of your life. Yeah. I don't use Facebook much anymore,
I think because of the fact that through COVID and then into 2021, I am doom scrolling a lot.
But there's a woman that was a graduate from my high school a couple of years before me,
and she actually, I think only the two people from my hometown are up in the Boston area now
that I know of. She's a very well-respected doctor at MGH, and she just put out the PSA
to everyone in the group and said, this is real. I'm seeing patients. It's pretty ugly.
This is real. The lockdown is probably longer than, it's probably longer than two weeks.
You might be looking at it toward the end of the year, and that was shocking to me.
But I believed her, and so I started preparing for that mentally and supply-wise, and in every way
that I could, started preparing for that eventuality. I remember the guidelines slowly started coming
out, six feet social distancing, masks, and you start to kind of reset how you think about
just being in the community. You don't want to be in the household days. You go out for a walk,
but then you see someone across the street, and you are giving each other the evil eye.
Why? Because for all you know, this person could be the end of me. If this person runs up and says,
hi, it could be over. Those were the sorts of wild thoughts going through our heads at the time.
I think that the hardest part was you didn't know how to gauge risk, just because everything
was unknown. We didn't know how well masks worked. I think now we know that they did very well,
and social distancing certainly worked as well. But we also implemented some measures that in
hindsight just did not make sense at all. I was one of the many people who would go to the grocery
store, load up on dry goods, and then before I brought them in my house, I had to wipe them
all down with alcohol. My fingers were just decimated all year from Clorox wipes until I
found out that wasn't necessary. I remember the thing that hit me was I started learning about
viral shedding and that younger kids especially seemed to largely be asymptomatic, but that they
just shed and shed and they shed a lot of virus. So if you held a baby or a young kid up to your face,
you could just be getting a devastating amount of COVID that your system is not ready for.
You had a two-year-old at the time, so it was pretty scary. I think it might be a good time to
talk about the concept of bubbling. It was a tough time for everybody, but I think kids especially.
Two years old, that's a major time in life to start developing social skills. With one child
at home, it was just, what do we do? We were fortunate that we were able to find a family
with similar-aged kids. They had similar risk tolerances as us, similar testing policies,
and we just found this nice connection where the kids could get together and hang out.
I would drive every week to urgent care and get swabbed and make sure that I was
still negative. That just became the norm for a long time.
Yeah. It was a strange time because you almost had a bifurcation.
At the time, we were living in Arlington. It was a relatively dense neighborhood.
One of the things that happened was when lockdown happened, people went outside. I actually met a
whole lot of neighbors, obviously from a distance that I had not met before, just because people
didn't have anything else to do. People would go outside. They would talk from a distance again
at the local park. I actually met a lot of people that I, even though I had lived in that house for
I think a number of years, had not even seen them. Never mind had met them. That was,
I guess, different. For kids, I had a sixth grader, a fifth grader, and a second grader.
The kids got hit pretty hard because when you're a kid, you need to be social. That is an
incredibly strong urge. When you're trying to keep kids apart, it's just really tough.
Fortunately, we had a household of three so they could play with each other.
I think that helped them a lot. Being restricted to play with their friends,
that was definitely difficult. I remember seeing at the local playgrounds, because they shut down
all the colleges, they basically just sent all the kids home the first couple of weeks of lockdown.
You had a lot of college students, high schoolers as well, that parents just could not restrain.
Their urge, obviously, at that age is to go be social. You tell a group of high schoolers
that, no, you can't get together and be social and pick up basketball and go do stuff. It's
really tough. That's really tough. You're someone like the bad guy from Footloose.
Yeah, exactly. They were pushing the limits of social distancing as far as they could.
Absolutely.
Rightfully so. I remember thinking to myself, okay, I think we can probably socially distance
and lockdown for maybe two or three months. After that, I think just human beings are social
creatures. They need to be around each other. After that, there's just no way.
Yeah. It slowly started to emerge for us personally too. I had golf before in my life,
but I started playing a lot more golf because it was really easy to be distant.
A lot of fires in the backyard and a solo stove, solo stoves with some neighbors. I had
moved here relatively recently when this all started and had moved here when my son was
nine months old. That year and a quarter, I hadn't met a ton of people yet. I was just starting to
come out of that early baby time. I have friends now where it's hard to remember this, but I have
friends in my neighborhood here that I knew for a year before I stepped foot in their house. My
in-laws moved nearby and it was a year before we would go to their yard and play and they would be
up on the porch and we'd be talking 30 feet away. It was really just so strange.
You got pretty good at having outdoor meals under heaters.
Yes. There's this Concord Family Network and a friend of mine and I, three weeks before
COVID hit, had taken responsibility to organize Dad's Night Out. All of a sudden we're at,
okay, how do we do this? We're locked down for the year. We organized all these.
There was a Children's Cafe and they organized, oh, we'll just put together a meal for you and
a beer sampler or whiskey sampler and you can all go on Zoom and try all these things together and
talk about them. There was a fun part there of just making the best of it and trying to meet people.
It's worth talking about the virtual life that we all went from reality to virtual reality
to Zoom overnight. Overnight to Zoom, yeah. I was thinking about this the other day.
There are a few key pieces of technology that if they weren't around during COVID,
I don't know how we would have made it. One of the biggest ones was obviously being able to
communicate via the internet but being able to do so virtually as well and do so seamlessly with
some honestly awesome software. It allowed a lot of people just to go home on one day and then the
next day flip open their laptops, rejigger their home office. I think a lot of couples, a lot of
families went through the growing pains of trying to figure out where exactly the home offices are
and are not in order to not be disrupted by kids, by pets, by spouses. Going through that process,
you were suddenly going from talking to people all day to just staring at a computer screen all day,
just overnight. People did that really quickly. Did you pick up any weird hobbies during COVID?
Yeah. Let's see. I did. I got into woodworking more. I remember, while I don't think we did this,
there were certain trends that you would see where suddenly everyone was into something,
then everyone was into something else. I think one of the first trends that came around was
sourdough bread. Absolutely. Yeah. I remember people naming their sourdough starters. There's
Vladimir Gluten. I can't remember all the ones that came out. My buddy Matt, who we did the
Conquer Family Network thing, he's an awesome guy. He's a rugby player, so he's just a big
jacked guy. That's not the typical profile somebody that you think is, he's an excellent,
excellent cook, very good cook. He bought five pounds of bread flour. He was like,
there's no way to throw all this. He came and split it with me. We went back and forth,
hey man, I'm making bagels today. We're sharing recipes. I would say that on a scale from one to
10, my wife and I went from being 0.5 out of 10 to, we're a solid five now. We definitely
got better because at the beginning in concrete, the door dash team was basically 0. It's grown a
ton now. There are a lot of options you can get, but take out and delivery just wasn't really a
thing around here. It was a lot of home cooking. That's right. That's a good point actually,
because lockdown happened. Suddenly, everyone was cooking three meals a day. You had to brush off
your skill set and relearn how to do that if you weren't before. There was also, you talk
about people who got hit pretty hard, the restaurants. It was like a surgical strike
on the service community. Yeah. A lot of my favorite places in the Boston area are gone now.
Yeah. I think there was certainly a lot of goodwill and people trying to help out restaurants by
going above and beyond to order out. Certainly, it wasn't enough for a lot of places,
but restaurants, you talk about just trying to figure out how to survive.
They went from having a full room to, if they're lucky, and they had enough of a cash cushion,
suddenly turning into a delivery only business. Then you had pretty strong
emergence of these food delivery services. Yeah. Well, you ever go to Red Bones in Summerville,
Fair Square? Yeah. That's transformed from, you never could get delivery from there,
but that was a hotspot. It was a hangout spot, lunch and dinner. I went there,
and I went there a month ago with a buddy of mine. When I lived in Davis Square, I used to go there
once a week. It's almost purely takeout now. It's actually kind of odd if you're there eating.
Is it the whole order with a QR code type? Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah. That's new as well. I think that- QR code.
A touchless ordering. Yeah.
Necessity is the mother of invention. It didn't go out to be true.
Just to give a sense of how desolate it was outside of people's houses, I remember it was in,
it must have been in probably late March. No, it must have been in April at some point.
I took the family. We were going completely stir crazy. We decided to drive to my sister's house
who lives in Brookline. We took the long way just because we were curious to see what the city looked
like. We saw maybe a car the entire way driving from Arlington all the way to Brookline. It was
not even people outside. People were inside. It was so eerie.
Yeah. It's eerie. I remember driving into Boston
times and just being like, it's not supposed to take 15 minutes to get into Boston.
No. Yeah, it's crazy.
I don't think we'll see that unless, I mean, knock on wood, I can't imagine another scenario
where we'll see that. Yeah. I will say that I do have two Bonsai trees as a result of
the pandemic. I got a jade and a juniper. There's a store Bonsai West in Hatton. It's really cool.
I tried to get a pine, but they wouldn't let me. They're like, you're too much of a beginner.
You're just going to kill it. They're like, if you can pass the juniper, then you can get a pine.
Yeah. Sadly, I named them Leroy and Jenkins because I was just,
if anyone knows the Leroy Jenkins story, it's a story of just going into something
guns a blazing without any real forethought into the fact that I'm probably not very good
taking care of plants. These plants will be alive in 50 years, right?
Unfortunately, Juniper Jenkins did not make it. Oh, no.
But Leroy, Leroy the Jade is thriving and I took one, I clipped off a branch and planted it
in Juniper Jenkins soil and that one is growing now too. Yeah, it's a baby.
So that was kind of fun. I needed something kind of peaceful to do. So it was a good time. I know
a lot of people picked up some weird hobbies. I'd love to, if anyone listening to this wants
to let us know, let me know. I've heard about rock polishing.
Oh yeah. I think that was one of the most
surprising hobbies that I heard about. Like that actually sounds very, very calming.
Well, I feel like when I was kind of eight to 12 year old zone, like any museum or any kind of
like kids friendly place that we went to, there were rock polishing kits. I bet, I think a lot
of us probably like kind of went back to things that are comfortable to us at the time. To me,
like I am total amateur armchair psychologist. I've never even took a psychology course and I'm
fascinated by the subject. I'm just fascinated about the raw human responses to some of this stuff
from seeking comfort to, you know, I think the response of some of the public to basically just
deny that this was happening at all until it hit them directly is that's just a human subconscious
response to something of just how to react to an existential threat. I actually heard a really
interesting story today. I was listening to some history of Omaha Beach D-Day and they were saying
that these guys, despite all their training, they just went into this subconscious response of they're
getting machine gun fire at them and it's just, you know, the ninth level of hell. And there's this
human response when something happens and you just start digging a hole. To get in the hole
and just wait until it's over and then come back out. And it's like people were digging holes
under the water and it made absolutely no logical sense on this reaction to it. But this is just a
human response. I think that the word head in the sand was used a lot for, I think, groups of people
who were just like, no, this isn't happening. It's not real. And I think that that, I'm not saying
as a political thing or anything like that, I just think it's fascinating the human response
to something like this happening. And I think we all had interesting things happen to us in
different mental states during this time. So it was definitely kind of wild. I think maybe part of the
reason why we blocked out so many memories when we were talking about doing this.
No, I definitely, I probably went hoarse a few times yelling at the TV in the early days.
Just given the background.
So, yeah, we went through kind of like the social stuff and maybe we can bring back to the science.
So I know you were saying that we know coronavirus. We found out pretty quickly what this was.
Yeah. What's the pathway then to vaccines, treatments, like how, from a scientific
standpoint, what are you looking for and how are these things created and why mRNA?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely. So with COVID-19, we actually, because of SARS 1, we had in a little
bit of a weird way, a bit of a leg up. So SARS 1 came out early 2000s and what, and I think it
put on the radar the fact that coronaviruses are nasty. I mean, very high likelihood that at some
point in human history, another coronavirus pandemic is going to come and hit us pretty hard.
And that kind of triggered surveillance programs. I think that there are some,
actually now infamous surveillance programs that were established in Asia.
There was also a lot of basic research that went into trying to figure out how best to generate
a good immune response against essentially pieces of coronavirus. So I think
I think vaccinology for years has generally taken the form of taking bits of a virus, whether
it's an inactivated dead virus or whether it's recombinant pieces of a virus, essentially
proteins that are directly derived from a virus that have identified to elicit a very good immune
response. Kind of mixing that with at times another agent that can kind of ramp up the immune
response at the same time, and then you use it as a vaccine. And I mean, we all get childhood vaccines.
We don't really talk about measles, mumps, rubella, diphtheria, tetanus, polio, meningitis
anymore because we get vaccinated against those as children. Smallpox isn't around anymore as a
result, et cetera. So they're extremely effective. And with vaccines, usually the whole drug discovery,
drug development process, it takes on the order of decades, not years, decades. It usually takes
minimum 10 years to come up with a good vaccine, then run all of the clinical trials first in
healthy humans, and then just identify safety, and then phase two, phase three. And finally,
you get approval, and then you'll get a large pharmaceutical company like a Pfizer
to manufacture hundreds of millions of doses, almost never billions, to be honest,
but usually hundreds of millions of doses for peak sales. So vaccines are viewed as,
and they have for a while, as probably the best weapon that we could ever elicit against a pandemic.
Now, what happened with COVID-19, there was a few kind of just underlying insights that were
generated that we didn't know what at the time kind of set us up for success. One was the
development of mRNA technology. And I think it's been an idea that's been kicked around for a while,
where rather than taking bits of a virus, either recombinant protein that's directly derived from
a virus or a heat-inactivated virus, why don't we take a step back and use mRNA, which actually
encodes the protein, and deliver that to a patient in order to vaccinate. And it's an idea that
could apply not just to vaccinations, but also diseases like protein replacement, diseases like
chemophilia. Can we use mRNA, administer it to a patient, and have it express monoclonal antibodies,
which are used as a therapeutic as well, quite broadly. So with vaccines, that idea was definitely
out there. I think at the time, there was probably a notion that mRNA-based vaccines,
in the instance of a pandemic, could be a technology that could be quickly turned around
and used. And you had a couple of companies, one being BioNTech, the other being Moderna,
that established a lot of the research, establishing that this could be done, certainly
in preclinical animal models, and I think at least in early-stage clinical development. So the
technology, I think, was maybe not ready for prime time, but it's probably at the brink,
ready for prime time. Also, a lot of the basic science that was done in support of figuring out
and studying SARS-1 was directly applicable to COVID-19. One good example is that there was
some really nice work that came out of labs from collaboration from Scripps, NIH, and actually
Dartmouth, where they used the spike protein. I think everyone who has gone through the pandemic
now knows that there's something on COVID called the spike protein. And it's basically...
It's the key to entry to the cell, yeah.
Exactly. Exactly. If you think of COVID virus particles as a golf ball, exactly, the spike
protein is what attaches to the cell, it allows the virus to actually get in. It's also
a bit of the Achilles heel of the virus, because that's what the immune response tends to recognize,
at least antibodies that are generated. So it's a very good target to generate vaccines against.
And so there was some work where it was initially observed that the spike protein
in SARS and MERS was actually very floppy. It didn't express well. When you tried to
express the protein and use it in the context of a vaccine, it just didn't generate a good
immune response. So they identified a couple of point mutations that they could make, just
switching a couple of amino acids in the spike protein that made it a lot more rigid. And those
mutations ultimately ended up in both the Moderna and Pfizer, the BioNTech Pfizer products. And if
that insight hadn't been made, if mRNA technology kind of wasn't at the brink of prime time,
I don't think we would have had a COVID vaccine.
Yeah. So you had...
We'd still be in it.
We certainly...
Unless it mutated down to...
It would be... There would be, I mean, a lot, under the order of millions more people that
would be dead, unfortunately, if we hadn't had that. And so you had mRNA vaccines kind of at the
brink of prime time. You had these insights as to what exactly the target from a vaccine standpoint
and what both Moderna and Pfizer did as soon as the sequence was available. I think this was in
January at some time. They were just off to the races. And they basically reduced
10 years of drug discovery and drug development into about nine months. They were dosing patients
in a matter of months for phase one. And they evaluated multiple vaccine candidates in parallel
and at risk started manufacturing, or at least establishing the manufacturing footprint needed
to manufacture vaccines first for phase three, they'd just skip phase two, into phase three,
and then for commercial development. So I was actually in the Pfizer trial.
Yeah, you were early.
Yeah, I was early.
And how nervous were you?
So it's a good question. I was not actually. And I know, and this is where I probably benefited
a little bit just from my knowledge of mRNA, because I knew the components of the vaccine,
it was a lipid nanoparticle, which is basically a little bit of grease. It's very similar chemical
composition to what the membranes of our cell contain today. It's really no different. So I
wasn't worried about that. mRNA is mRNA. It's a genetic code that is highly transient.
If it enters your cells, it's usually gone within a few days. But it certainly does a lot of business
while it's in the cell. So honestly, I wasn't that worried. I was actually pretty excited.
Are you bonded that you didn't get superpowers?
I am actually. I was expecting some more of a like activity. And so, I mean, I remember actually
going in for my first appointment. What month was this?
This would have been in August, actually.
August 2020.
Yeah, August 2020.
Wow. Yeah. So five months after we knew it was real.
Exactly. And I actually calculated, I was within the first 10,000 days of the vaccine.
10,000 patients dosed. Yeah. Within the first 10 for the Pfizer.
And you didn't know at the time if you had actually gotten a vaccine or if it was placebo?
Had no idea.
And you were instructed just live your life as you normally would.
Exactly.
And we're going to keep testing you.
They viewed me as high risk because I had kids.
And because we lived fairly close to Boston. And so, got the shot, felt nothing. Carried on with
my life. I was a little bummed that I didn't feel anything because that hinted to me that I might
have gotten placebo rather than the vaccine. Then 21 days later, got a second shot. Also felt nothing.
Was also bummed that I didn't feel anything because that confirmed to me at least that I thought.
Because they told you you might be sore or feel out of it or something.
Yeah. I thought I would have felt something because usually when you get vaccines,
your arm is like flu vaccine. Your arm is usually kind of sore.
Yeah. Yeah.
And so-
And I've heard that lipid nanoparticle, I mean it's nanoparticle, it's actually fairly big
as a delivery device that it can make. That's kind of what makes you tired and sore.
And so, yeah.
It's good at eliciting immune responses. So lipid nanoparticles are generally the size of a virus.
Yeah.
And so, one of the major innovations that was made that kind of led mRNA vaccines to actually be real
was at a Nobel Prize was given to Drew Weissman and Carolyn Catalanco. They identified how to
de-immunize mRNA. So to make it not elicit an immune response by changing particular,
making chemical changes in the actual nucleic acid. And that actually was kind of the key.
Because otherwise your body would recognize the mRNA that was administered and reject it.
Attack it, yeah.
So what they figured out was a way to essentially mask it from the human immune system. It would
allow it to then essentially be translated into whatever protein it was supposed to translate.
But the LNP portion actually did serve as a good immune enhancing
adjuvant, which is why the vaccines just work so well.
Yeah, great.
So with...
Did anything change after the trial to the one that you got then the one that I got?
Did anything change in terms of density of mRNA delivered or anything like that?
I think they changed... Yeah, so the first... First off, the vaccine was 90% effective for...
I think it was called the Wuhan strain.
Wow.
Then they realized that other strains are on the horizon. So because coronavirus is a
positive RNA stranded virus, it has a tendency to undergo a low rate of mutational change.
And that was manifest in subsequent strains of COVID, unfortunately. I think the big ones were
Delta, where you had a couple of mutations in the spike region. Then the big one was Omicron,
which hit us really hard about a year after the pandemic first started, where you had some
additional changes that... And those changes, what they tended to do was evade our existing
immune response as well as to some of the vaccines from the get go. So with the vaccines,
what they had to do first was rather than two shots, providing a third shot would then bring
our immunity back up to level between the Wuhan strain and the Delta strain. So two shots, 90%
activity against the Wuhan strain, but there's a drop off for Delta. You give a third shot,
then you're able to boost immunity back up to the Delta strain. But the problem is that COVID is
going to continue to mutate and work to evade the immunity that the vaccines were able to elicit.
So Omicron, we actually had to get a tweak, the actual sequence of the mRNA within the virus in
order to make it better match the Omicron strain. Cool. Yeah. I'm trying to follow along as much
as I can. As I've been... I've gotten all my boosters and everything. I've been a good boy.
I have two questions left. One is, you told me a story that I think would be awesome if you shared
it. You Mr. Wizarded your own testing. How does that work? Yeah. So in the early days of the
pandemic, being able to access tests was an issue. I think I mentioned earlier that we were largely
blind. So the first test I ever had, I think it was through a commercial vendor. I'm guessing it
was in the spring at some point. Things were so chaotic that they never sent me the results.
I think I paid like a hundred bucks out of pocket and it just never showed up. So
being able to access a good COVID test was a major, major problem. And they also were not cheap.
So one of the benefits of being in biotech is you have a lot of like-minded individuals around you
that kind of egg each other on and encourage you to kind of operate at the edges. So we set up...
I actually set up together with a couple of my biotech friends, kind of a home testing
system where I purchased a early 90s vintage PCR machine. It was a very, very cheap machine.
A PCR machine which allows you to do the thermo-cycling that is required in order to amplify
the actual nucleic acid regions of COVID. So I purchased it on eBay for, believe it or not,
like 150 bucks, which I'm actually to this day, I'm surprised it was so inexpensive.
It was definitely an early model where I actually had to think folks, scientists,
we'll get the reference, actually had to use mineral oil and apply it on top of the reaction
just because that's how archaic the PCR machine was. So worked with a couple of my biotech
colleagues to procure reagents. And we actually pooled funds, we shared reagents. And we would
essentially optimize protocols in parallel to each other and kind of share tips as to what the best
possible protocol could be. And what this meant was is that anytime, and the example I'll use is
when my brother was visiting from out of town and we're about to get together for Easter.
Brother came into town. Before he basically came into our house, we had him swab as well as his
family. We did a quick PCR test on our kitchen counter. I'm sitting there with my gloves,
literally on my kitchen counter. Tests came up negative. Okay, you can come into the house.
Then we tested them again the next day before we went to go visit my parents. And
the lengths that you would go through just to make sure that you were clean before you were
visiting family, I mean, people would crawl through mud in order to get there just to make sure
that things were safe. Yeah, absolutely. Yeah, we had the same deal when my mom and stepdad came out
to visit. And first time they came out, totally innocuous, nothing happened. Second time they came
out, two days in, I had a scratchy throat. I took a test and that turned out positive. So I just ran
out of the basement, called them an Uber and they were on the next flight back at that point.
And it was just like, I felt awful. And you feel guilty. You feel guilty. Like, what did I just do?
You know, and I'm like, this is my mom and my stepdad. I don't want to be responsible for them
getting seriously ill. And yeah, my stepdad, they both ended up catching COVID. Both ended up being
fine. My mom got hit pretty hard by it and I just felt awful. But I think everyone has a similar
story from that time. You feel like an idiot for getting sick. I don't even know where I got it.
Probably wasn't working out the groceries hard enough.
So one thing I wanted to cover before we wrap up is looking into 2074.
Hopefully there's not another pandemic before then, but if one hits 2074,
give them some tips. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I mean, hopefully this doesn't happen. Unfortunately,
I actually think we kind of got lucky with this one. I know, I'm just going to not to bring everyone
down, but the fact is, is that the mortality rate for COVID was actually pretty low. If you think
about the mortality rates that we've touched on for the 1918 flu, as well as SARS-1, we actually
dodged a little bit of a bullet. And it was a bit of a highlight that I think that there's certain
areas that we definitely could have done better in terms of preparation. The good news is that
it certainly shed light on the need to be very vigilant upfront, just making sure that you have
mass testing, that you're able to track it. Because we just did. And we lost some weeks as a result.
The mRNA technology is certainly not going anywhere. It's an incredibly powerful tool,
I think, in our arsenal. It also is going to evolve. I was thinking about what times of crisis like
COVID, what it catalyzes. And I think a good analogy could be, you think about the technical
innovations that came about just because of World War II, or just because of the Cold War.
I mean, for World War II, you had computers, you had nuclear power, radar. From the Cold War,
you had a lot of just major leaps and bounds based off of that foundational technology.
I think for COVID-19, we're probably going to see at least something analogous. Maybe not something
similar, but something analogous, at least to add to our arsenal.
Yeah. It's incredible what humans can do. I mean, give someone a task in a deadline,
they can do it. And in times of crisis, the deadline is always tomorrow.
Yeah.
So, and it is incredible to me to hear you say something that should have taken a decade,
as we can condense down to you had it in five months.
It's incredible. I mean, what Pfizer-Moderna did is incredible. I mean, the way I look at it is,
no matter what, biology will win. Like at the end of the day, and I think there was a famous,
more popular slogan that science will win. I think that might have been Pfizer's tag line.
But anyway, I'll call it biology will win, just so it's not necessarily an advertisement for
Pfizer here. But the reality is biology will win. The virus is going to figure out a way to do what
it's going to do. And the big question is, how can you actually harness that biology for good?
How can you figure out what the Achilles heel of that particular biology could be and make
it work for you rather than against you?
Yeah. Awesome. Well, this has been amazing. I think we had other stuff that was on the list,
but I don't want to go too long. Anyone with my attention span isn't going to make it past here.
But this has been great, very educational. A trip down memory dark alley.
A little bit of PTSD there.
Yeah, a little bit. But I think we all had interesting times. I think everyone had
lost during the time. I thought it would be good to talk about this from those different points
of view and just cover it. So I hope it's been educational and 2075 humans.
Yeah.
I hope you're healthy and happy.
Hopefully your health care workers and your scientists are as dedicated and hardworking
and self-sacrificing as they were. If you ever do go through this again,
as they were at this time around.
Absolutely. Well, thanks so much and we'll sign off and get back to the daily thing.